<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<!--
  categories: Play Report, Playable, Misc, WIP, Worldbuilding, Not Review, Discourse
-->
<channel>
  <title>Seedling Games Blog</title>
  <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blog.html</link>
  <description>On creating, publishing and playing TTRPGs. Also worldbuilding. </description>
  <language>en-ca</language>

  <item>
    <title>On Religion (Belated Conclave Blog Edition) </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/worldbuilding/religion_misc.html</link>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2 class="title">On Religion (Belated Conclave Blog Edition)</h2> <p>Here are some miscellaneous ideas that were supposed to be for the the <a href="https://prismaticweekly.substack.com/p/emergency-bandwagon-conclave-edition">conclave blog</a> thing.</p> <p>The problem is I tried to just polish up some existing notes and then started writing a new Cairn 2e background (which I've given up on for now) and next thing you know there was a pope and it was too late.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Part 1: Falsehoods Worldbuilders Believe About Religion</h2> <p>This is a reference to <a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2010/06/17/falsehoods-programmers-believe-about-names/">&quot;falsehoods programmers believe about names&quot;</a>.</p> <p>I have a non-Christian religious background, both religiously and culturally. I tend to not talk about my own cultural background these days. But it is fairly notable that people tend to think that all religions are one of the following two religions:</p> <ul> <li>Christianity</li> <li>A specific set of Ancient Greek beliefs as understood in pop culture.</li> </ul> <p>So here is an extremely incomplete list of falsehoods worldbuilders often believe about religion, based on a combination of people I have known and their beliefs and a lot of time spent on wikipedia. I'm a bit reluctant to name specific religions as inspiration for these, because a lot of what I'm thinking of is not just the beliefs of a particular religion, but the beliefs of a particular religion as believed by a particular culture in a particular point in time, which probably doesn't fully represent what other people believe.</p> <h2 class="subsubtitle">The Actual List (of Falsehoods)</h2> <ul> <li>You can only follow one religion at a time.</li> <li>Religions have gods.</li> <li>Religions have holy texts.</li> <li>Religions have a canonical set of beliefs that everyone agrees on.</li> <li>It is important that members of a religion believe the correct things.</li> <li>Gods have human attributes.</li> <li>Gods have a physical form on some level of existence.</li> <li>Gods created the world.</li> <li>There is a clear distinction between gods and other supernatural beings.</li> <li>Gods dictate correct and incorrect behaviour.</li> <li>Gods need or want followers.</li> <li>Religions believe that the faithful are rewarded after death.</li> <li>Religions care about faith, as a concept.</li> <li>Religions believe that good people are rewarded after death.</li> <li>Religions believe that bad people are punished after death.</li> <li>Religions describe an afterlife at all.</li> <li>Religions desire converts.</li> <li>Religions allow converts.</li> <li>Religion is clearly distinct from culture; you can always easily determine what beliefs or actions are religious and which are secular.</li> <li>Religions which enforce strong social norms align with modern, conservative notions of those social norms.</li> <li>Conversely, religions which do not align with modern, conservative notions of social norms do not have strict social norms.</li> <li>Religion is a well-defined concept.</li> </ul> <img class="blog-image-small-heading" src="worldbuilding/img/abstract_religion.png" alt="an abstract, geometric, symmetric drawing"> <h2 class="title">Part 2: Religion In My Implied Setting</h2> <p>I'm slowly settling on a vaguely defined, implied setting in at least half of what I do. It especially exists in my solo Cairn games but you may recognise aspects of it in other things I have written.</p> <p>Despite listing all of that above, I am not going to do anything wildly unconventional, to set expectations.</p> <p>Religions in my vaguely defined setting. I am actually not going to do anything terribly unconventional, despite the above list. This default setting mostly exists in my solo games but also to some degree in some of the adventures I write I guess, and more in the things I haven't written.</p> <h1 class="subtitle">What gods are like</h1> <p>I like having gods be local: beings of power that you can deal with directly, like factions. They're usually weird and capricious, with motivations not in line with mortal concerns. They exist on a spectrum with spirits and other supernatural forces: the difference is that they are more powerful, and they intrinsically effect the world around them in some way.</p> <p>In particular, gods can die, but it permanently changes the world, usually for the worse. If the god of a river dies, the river runs dry. If the good of the deer of the forest die, the deer sicken and die and then there are no more deer. If the god who watches over the village dies, calamity after calamity happens until the village is abandoned.</p> <p>There are important gods as well, like the gods of the sun, but these are above most adventurers' paygrade. A large city will have a temple to the sun, and the priests will make offerings to encourage it to keep rising, but that's probably not your problem. You are unlikely to personally have any issues with the sun, or any problems you can reasonably ask the sun to solve. There might be holidays around the god of the sun. In that way they are a lot like an emperor: the emperor's coronation day might be a holiday, but you have little direct interaction with them. The gods you deal with are more like local nobility.</p> <p>Gods generally do not have gender as we understand it. They do not have a physical form, but have small areas of strong influence (e.g. a temple or a holy site), and large areas of weak influence (e.g. a forest or a village). They may occasionally manifest a physical form in those areas and often have several shapes that they prefer taking.</p> <h2 class="subsubtitle">Some Cairn rules</h2> <p>The way I've been modelling their power in Cairn is assigning them some spells they can basically cast as much as they want within their areas of influence. Some they can cast only in their areas of strong influence. They can directly intercede in mortal affairs, but their scope is limited. Clerics do not intrinsically have access to these spells, but may be better at asking for help from their gods in areas of power.</p> <p>Some gods:</p> <ul> <li>The deer god of deer mountain. Appears as a deer with golden antlers. Will only allow those it deems worthy to hunt its deer - otherwise trespassers are trampled to death. <ul> <li>Spells anywhere on the mountain: Anthropomorphise, auditory illusion, hatred (on deer), frenzy (on deer)</li> <li>Spells in its holy glade: Beast form (Cast on someone else), Command, Cure wounds, pacify. Can also cure any contagious disease.</li> </ul> </li> <li>The god of the village of Cold Rock. A very old rock in the middle, that is always cold to the touch. A shrine was built around it. The god wants to protect the village from danger from outside - or what it thinks is danger. <ul> <li>Spells anywhere in the village: control weather, earthquake, fog cloud, phobia</li> <li>Spells next to its shrine: ward, snuff, raise spirit, icy touch</li> </ul> </li> <li>The East Wind of the Straits of Tears. Sailors make an offering before passing through this perilous route so that the winds don't dash them against the rocks. This god, it is said, is easily offended, with certain words being best avoided. Many do not speak at all after the sacrifice is made. <ul> <li>Spells: control weather, that's all it needs.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h2 class="subtitle">Clerics</h2> <p>Clerics and priests and so on generally don't go adventuring because they usually have daily responsibilities and are expected to remain respectable. Adventuring is not really respectable.</p> <p>Clerics, as mentioned, don't get spells from their gods, but religions as institutions are more likely to have access to spellbooks and are especially likely to have thematically appropriate ones. In general, a cleric's power comes from being part of a long-lasting institution with political importance: from the loyalty of their followers, the wealth of the institution, their importance to mortal power, and maybe some relevant artifacts. Clerics are also likely to be educated, and to have access to secret knowledge.</p> <h2 class="subsubtitle">Extremely WIP Cairn cleric background</h2> <p>I started writing a cairn class for an ex-cleric, but I ran out of time. There is exactly one table, not even complete, that I think is worth sharing at the m:</p> <p>Why are you no longer a priest?</p> <ol> <li>At your temple, a priesthood lasts 7 years, and now it's done.</li> <li>Your temple was destroyed, sacked. Perhaps you have sworn revenge, or perhaps you want to rebuild it elsewhere.</li> <li>You were assigned to the priesthood as a child, but as an adult, wished to see beyond its walls and fled.</li> <li>You were kicked out due to corruption: asking for bribes, or stealing from temple offerings.</li> <li>You were kicked out due to heresy: your beliefs were unconventional, or your temple lost a political battle, or political reforms forced uniformity on the religion. You were forced to flee, or ordered into exile.</li> <li>You are still a priest, but you belong to a remote temple of a minor god and your duties are limited. You do weddings, births and funerals, and a few yearly holidays, but otherwise you need to find other ways to make ends meet.</li> </ol> <img class="blog-image-small-heading" src="worldbuilding/img/abstract_bird.png" alt="an abstract drawing of a bird"> <h2 class="title">Part 3: Types of Gods</h2> <p>I don't really like the usual fantasy domains, because they seem mostly based on a limited set of real world religions and also not have a lot to do with how people live their lives and what is important to them. Like probably a lot of religions have a god associated with &quot;thunder&quot; but I think it was not necessarily one of the most important things people would have a god for. But having sets of domains is convenient for designing games. So here's an alternative set</p> <ol> <li>Gods of the state. The sun, the king, humans who become gods, etc. They represent power and authority, justice and the law. They are most concerned with right and wrong, and their followers are most likely to have institutional power. They are most likely to be hierarchical in nature and to require uniformity in belief. Paladin-types would be associated with these, whether they represent justice or tyranny. You are most likely to deal with this god's representatives, rather than this god directly.</li> <li>Gods associated with sustenance. Gods of farming and the harvest, the seasons, the hunt, the rivers and the sea. Everyday gods, maybe small and local ones. Celebrated in festivals that mark the rhythm of the years. Of most immediate concern to ordinary people. Clerics may be more informal, more embedded in the community, with more regional customs and more differences from village to village.</li> <li>Chthonic gods: gods of the underworld, of death, of curses and oaths and vengeance. Perhaps gods that go unnamed, that are propitiated rather than worshipped. Feared, but not necessarily evil. Death is a part of life. Laws may also fall under their domain, but only the oldest laws, laws even the gods fear to break.</li> <li>Mystery gods. Gods of secrets, the knowledge of the universe. Books and monasteries, or initiation rituals and hidden places. Remote places, altered states of mind. Things only a few are meant to know. Old and forgotten gods, and gods that appeared yesterday. It's disappointing that this type of god is usually relegated to evil cults, because there is so much more that you can do that's interesting. </li> <li>Gods of the home. Your ancestors. The hearth. Children and childbirth. Sickness and health. A  home altar, or perhaps something small you carry with you as you travel. A mischievous spirit. Few priests: perhaps someone to bless your house when you lay its foundations, but it's everyone's individual responsibility otherwise.</li> <li>Gods of work. Of wealth and good fortune, of travelers and merchants, of artisans and skill. A god for a guild; for a marketplace; for a ship; for a harbour; for an old mill, or the winds that drive it; for the magic that keeps a blade sharp. These gods are very specific, and their worship is aligned with other institutions and traditions.</li> </ol> <h2 class="subsubtitle">Combining These</h2> <p>Picking some random combinations:</p> <ul> <li>gods of the state + mystery gods: A temple that only a select few can visit, the center of royal power, the place the ruler communes with the gods and thus gains the right to rule, would make an excellent dungeon.</li> <li>Gods of the home + gods of work: Certain jobs stay within certain families, the worship of the relevant god passed down from generation to generation. A mill, perhaps, where the last miller died, and now the mill is angry.</li> <li>Chthonic gods + mystery gods: almost too obvious a combination. But perhaps you have sworn to take revenge, or you must find a particular sword that can slay the dragon or something, and the only way you can do that is prove yourself in the dungeon of someone or other and gain an audience with a god at the gates to the underworld at the bottom.</li> </ul> <p>You could also have more than one god in each category. A village with a god of the fields, of the forest, and of the sea as their main gods (each falling under a god of sustenance) tells you something about how the town sees the world. A town with 4 gods representing 4 civic virtues (gods of the state) also tells you something about it. Maybe these gods aren't even considered to be supernatural beings, they are explicitly meant to be metaphorical. Contrast against one whose state religion consists of the patron god of three powerful families who compete for power. </p>]]></description>
        <category>WIP, Worldbuilding</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, May 10 2025</pubDate>
  </item>


  

  <item>
    <title> On NSR camp </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/discourse/nsr_camp.html</link>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I am way late on writing this up; I meant to write stuff after NSR camp 2, and write some stuff about playtesting, and now I largely have forgotten what I was going to say. I figure I should probably publish what I have before I forget everything, though.</p> <p class="subtitle">Previous History with Online Conventions</p> <p>NSR camp is not a convention, but it makes sense to talk about it in the context of online conventions.</p> <p>I've really enjoyed the online conventions I've been to. Typically at online conventions, as at regular conventions, I mostly take the opportunity to play a lot of games, especially games I otherwise wouldn't get to play.</p> <p>I've been to two - an RPGSEA one, and an Exalted Funeral one. Both were fairly early in the pandemic, but the idea kind of died off. I imagine they are a lot of work to put on, and that people started preferring to put that effort into meeting people IRL.</p> <p>For me, it's a lot easier for me to justify going to an online convention over a physical one. There is basically just one in my area, despite living in a big city, and it has shut down at least for now. While I can afford to travel to a convention, I find it hard to justify that as well as taking time off work given that I'm not a big name author nor do I plan to be. I'm trying to limit the amount of flying I do. I often feel more comfortable playing with strangers online as I feel it's easier to make sure that I'm playing with a group I'm comfortable playing with (please don't yell at me about this one, this apparently makes some people pretty angry).</p> <p>There are also things I particularly liked about the online conventions. I find they tended to attract more people who are not big names, by their nature they tend to be more indie, they tend to better reflect the parts of the scene that interest me. I talked to people in countries I would be unlikely to normally meet.</p> <p>I could of course just schedule a bunch of online games, but scheduling is hard and committing the time is hard. Having a one off event makes me more inclined to make an effort to clear my calendar of lower priority things, or things that can be rescheduled.</p> <p class="subtitle">What I Did at NSR Camp</p> <p>This is specifically not quite a convention. It's just a weekend to play games. There are no panels, no vending sessions, etc. It's kept as simple as possible.</p> <p>I've managed to play one game and run one game the last two NSR camps (the first one, I had family in town so I missed it.) I've wanted to play more - I could definitely do 3-4 games in a weekend and did significantly more at Big Bad Con - but life has gotten in the way.</p> <p>For running games, I have mostly looked through my bookshelf of unplayed games, using this as an opportunity to try new things. The first time was Knights of the Road, which I basically wrote and playtested an adventure for. The adventure went really well, I think, and let me regain a fair bit of confidence GMing and writing adventures that I'd lost after the past year or so had left me with no time to keep up with that. I will eventually publish it, but probably not until late this year.</p> <p>The second time I didn't have the energy to prep so I did the Stygian Library, which I've now promised to run again in the future.</p> <p>I also got to play Lancer, which was pretty cool: that is one I've wanted to try for quite a while. I also played another one of the Borgs, which I'd fallen out of playing the last year or so.</p> <p>This also lead me to realize that 9-10 AM is a pretty good time to run a game. You have the whole rest of the day ahead of you, and you get people who usually can't make it because of time zones.</p> <p class="subtitle">General Thoughts on NSR Camp</p> <p>A decent number of people who have never played any kind of indie RPG end up showing up to these. I think it's a fairly non-intimidating way to get started. I also find games advertised online are rarely one-shots: scheduling something is a fair bit of work so I think people find it to be not worth it unless there are several sessions. So this is a good opportunity to try new things without a multi session commitment.</p> <p>It's also more accessible than an actual convention: it's free, you don't have to travel, etc. You don't get quite as much of the spontaneous conversation, but they have a channel open for general discussion. It was only active when I was online for one of the camps, though. This is still a relatively small event.</p> <p>I hope it can maintain a critical mass to keep going.  A problem we often have is not having enough players for many of the games people want to play. A lot of games end up being scheduled at roughly the same time, likely due to certain time zones being better represented than others. A bigger group would also make it easier for people to run less mainstream or more experimental games - these often don't fill up. My hope is that this grows over time, but I worry it might instead shrink.</p> ]]></description>
        <category>Discourse</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, May 4 2025</pubDate>
  </item>


  <item>
    <title> </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/other_games/haxen.html</link>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2 class="title">Haxen</h2> <p>This is I guess the third of my not-review reviews, in combination with a play report.</p> <p>Haxen is an interesting solo game. Most solo games tend to follow a handful of mechanics, or get fairly complicated; this one is mechanically simple and pretty unique.</p> <p>I play a lot of solo games when travelling alone. This one is pretty great for that as it is a slim 8 pages including the cover; it plays quickly, and it needs nothing aside from a pencil, eraser and maybe some additional paper. No dice and no cards.</p> <p>I didn't play this for a while because I was a bit sceptical of a diceless solo game. Dice or other forms of randomness in solo games tend to play the pretty important role of adding in some external contributions to the game; for keeping it from being just a matter of writing a story (which is fine, just not what I'm trying to do.)</p> <p>What it does instead is have you mark off runes on a matrix; the next result is the next rune but in some cases you can jump ahead and mark any rune. The runes correspond roughly to a full success, a partial success and a failure; full successes are rare. Everything is done by marking a rune, the matrix is relatively small, and if it fills up, you die, making it a fast, tense game. There are limited ways to clear used runes while on an expedition, and on returning safely, there are a lot more ways to do so.</p> <p>I also have generally had trouble playing more mechanical, delve-y types of games solo, I have found they tend to feel overly mechanical, and not really capture my imagination or really make me care about the stakes. I've generally preferred playing systems not intended to be played solo in those cases, or solo journaling games. I did really enjoy this one though - probably due to the mechanics adding to the tension more effectively.</p> <p>I played two rounds of expeditions. An interesting side effect of the ability to erase runes between exploration sessions is that your chances of success will go way up the second time, because you are probably clearing the good runes. However, you have much fewer runes - and probably a few scars - and so you have even less time to succeed. My second expedition ended up feeling like effectively an epilogue to the first.</p> <p>Between expeditions, anything not named (which takes runes) disappears. I wasn't the biggest fan of that mechanic. Especially given how short each expedition was, and the fact that naming things literally shortens your life.</p> <p>As a side note this is described as being based on blades in the dark, which I find funny, because it is so much its own unique thing.</p> <p class="subtitle">Thoughts on hacks</p> <p>Some things I might try doing to hack this in the future/make it more campaign oriented:</p> <ul> <li>Have a separate rune matrix that can only be used for names and for anchors (forms of inspiration, like a spark table) <ul> <li>or maybe split things into a GM and a PC matrix. The GM one would also have lore, weather, locations, encounters and prophecy. This would mean that the more unique events are not competing against the player's chance of success - as it is, if you encounter more interesting things, you will probably fail at dealing with them.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Have a bigger set of runes, and the ability to clear more marked runes between expeditions</li> <li>Nothing is cleared between expeditions but you can enter at any part of the map</li> </ul> <p>At some point here I am basically proposing another game I guess - but I think this rune mechanic is interesting enough that it is worth doing. This game leaves me with a strong desire to play around with these mechanics more. Are there other games that use these? I guess it is creative commons so I could hack it. I think.</p> <p class="subtitle">The story</p> <p>The ranger Lazen, equipped with Rope and Bone, sets off into the Requiem to follow a bird with blood-red markings.</p> <p>It flies through skyscrapers. Lazen chases it, seeing glimpses of its plumage on the broken blue shards in the sky. It isn't until stumbling out of the expanse of skyscrapers that she notices a deep gash on her arm, the same red as the bird.</p> <p>She has lost sight of the bird, so she bandages it as best she can, and looks around at where she is - a river of crumbling black rock stretching in each direction, a flat scar on the land. A broken green sign says &quot;Orsi&quot;.</p> <p>A large machine sits on it, saying &quot;Ark&quot; on the side. Lazen climbs up and fiddles with it and it starts ponderously moving down the black river.</p> <p>It travels for a while, and then in the middle of the asphalt is a giant humming obsidian spear coming out of the ground, giving Lazen a horrible headache. She tries to get off the vehicle as it moves closer, but it's picked up speed now.</p> <p>She notices it's headed straight towards a pit, a giant hole in the ground around the monolith. She tries to jump out and falls. She grabs onto something - a lever - and the machine shudders to a halt - but the lever snaps and she falls, out of the vehicle and into the pit.</p> <p>The pit crackles with electricity. She sees a red bird, the red bird from before, and sees a way out, grabbing a strange object as she goes that fits in the palm of her hand. Did the bird guide her out?</p> <p>She follows it, but the air is full of lightning too, and a storm picks up. It has lead her to a crater, which perhaps is safer from the lighting? And in the crater is a tablet, saying - &quot;Find Gant, the sorcerer. He can help.&quot;</p> <p>After waiting out the storm, she heads back. This must be what the bird was to lead her to.</p> <p><em><strong>Part 2</strong></em></p> <p>She returns in triumph, but wounded. She thinks she can maybe at most take one more trip into the Requium, but she must find Gant.</p> <p>Some time passes and there is a new prophecy. He is among a field of flowers.</p> <p>She heads off in a direction where she has heard rumours of flowers. It is desert, however. She travels as fast as she can but finds herself weak and dizzy from the heat, from not enough water. Drained deeply, she knows she can't go much farther. And yet just beyond the deserts she sees a building. A church? A group of people there, who worship the sorcerer, Gant. She stumbles to their door and they look at her impassively.</p> <p>Eventually a man appears in robes. She asks if he is Gant, she says she hears he can help. (memetic hazard, a bit vague on how this applies) But he just raises his arms and says something, and somehow the world is reversed in some way. The crowd is gone, she is back in the desert, with a handful of flowers. She doesn't remember why she is there.</p> <p>She stumbles back home. She is greeted as though she returned triumphantly but she has no idea why. She says she walked through the desert and found flowers and they are talking about how they will send a group to go treat with Gant but she has no idea who Gant is. But when she says that it is as though they don't hear her.</p> ]]></description>
        <category>Play Report, Not Review</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, May 3 2025</pubDate>
  </item>


   <item>
    <title>What is a zine? And why? </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/discourse/what_is_a_zine.html</link>
        <description><![CDATA[ <h1 class="title">What's a zine? And why?</h1> <p>I'm going to ramble self-indulgently for a bit, feel free to skip to the next part.</p> <p>Last week, I went back home and was looking through some of my stuff from high school. I found the first zine I'd ever seen, given to me by another student, printed out on the school printer. It had never previously occurred to me that you could just make a book and call it something worth doing.  It also probably wasn't a coincidence that we were both queer, both closeted, though not particularly close, at a time when one simply could not be out in high school. I saw the hints of a possibility of a community that we defined ourselves, not one that was defined for us.</p> <p>At the time I had access to the Internet, but in a fairly limited way and it was pretty new. I read about making websites in a magazine about science for kids but couldn't actually do so. So for me this one single zine contained within it all of the possibilities that the Internet might have, if I had been born a few years later.  I wasn't part of a larger "scene" either. But this idea of a zine stuck with me for many years before I heard the word again.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Gatekeeping zines (keeping the gate open)</h2> <p>I want everyone to be able to make zines.</p> <p>I don't want to tell anyone that what they are making isn't a zine. If the word feels right to you, you're free to it. But I also don't want anyone to feel like what they're making <em>isn't good enough</em> to be a zine, because there's no such thing. The concept of a zine opens the door to people to create who are shut out of conventional publishing.</p> <p>So I won't ever tell someone that they are wrong to call something a zine, but I will tell you if your definition of a zine is wrong. Your definition of a zine is wrong, if:</p> <ul> <li>You think it needs professional, paid art on the cover or any interior page</li> <li>You think doodles or collages or random pieces of public domain art aren't good enough</li> <li>You think pages need to be bound nicely, or professionally printed</li> <li>You think the layout needs to be professional, to be done in layout software</li> <li>Maybe most controversially, if you think it needs editing</li> </ul> <p>A zine should have a barrier to entry no higher than a blog post.</p> <p>You probably haven't heard anyone actually explicitly say &quot;a zine requires editing&quot; or &quot;my art isn't good enough for a zine&quot;. This is probably something you've only heard a voice say inside your head. The gate that needs opening is the one inside your head.</p> <p>I'm not telling you <i>not</i> to do anything. Maybe you're really into fonts, or love doing layout. Maybe you are actually quite good at art. Maybe you have a relevant university degree. PoD doesn't need a big financial investment, and you can fund a Mixam print run by selling PDFs on itch. The point isn't that you aren't allowed to do those things, or that you need to achieve some platonic ideal of zine-hood. The point is that you don't <em>have</em> to. You are free of those constraints, and can freely pick the constraints that matter to you.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Why zines, though? Why do they matter?</h2> <p>Another thing to consider is, why were zines a thing? Before the Internet, they were a cheap and easy way of spreading ideas in a way that allows for many copies to be made. Zines didn't exist just because people really liked photocopy machines. Zines allowed books to be published without any gatekeepers. Conventional publishing limits who can access it. You need money and time, you need your idea to be respectable and marketable, you need to get your ideas past the gatekeepers of those who can own printing presses or brick and mortar stores.</p> <p>There are a lot of things that carry the spirit of zines without being zines. PDFs made with free software and posted on itch. Blog posts. Cheap personal websites. Google docs and shared spreadsheets.</p> <p>And there are other ways of making things more accessible, easier to spread. Creative commons publications, for instance. Games that are entirely markdown files. PDF files meant to be printed.</p> <p>The point actually isn't the format, although the format is fun and worthwhile. The point is the creative freedom.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">On non-corporate media</h2> <p>Every now and then someone makes a grand pronouncement about how we will free ourselves from corporations. We won't post on corporate social media, or use Kickstarter, or any of those things. And it never actually happens - because it's hard, it's too ambitious, and people give up. Yes, some people stick with it, but not the whole community.</p> <p>Part of the problem is that it is often phrased as an obligation, a sacrifice you have to make, a cause that's imposed on you. And so people don't follow through. And another part of the problem is that it is basically impossible to exist on the Internet these days entirely outside of corporate control, and I'm going to be honest, an extremely niche hobby is not going to transform the entire Internet. When it comes to generally trying to fix things in society, I spend 99% of my energy outside of the world of TTRPGs.</p> <p>Ask yourself instead, in what ways do you feel trapped or constrained? What non-corporate options make you excited about its possibilities? Maybe you feel you need corporate social media, but can create a space that you control by making your own website. Maybe you have to do Kickstarters to pay the bills or to just fulfill your dream of being published, but your blog gives you an outlet to share ideas without the constant pressure of marketability. Maybe it's learning to draw in this world of generative AI.  But most importantly, find something you love, that you care about, and not just something that someone on social media said you need to do.</p> <p>And maybe none of that is important to you. Personally, I think that's fine. But try and leave room for other people to find those things that are important to them, and maybe spend a bit of time cheering them on.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Related Work</h2> <p>A bunch of blog posts have been written recently on the general subject:</p> <p><a href="https://playfulvoid.game.blog/2025/01/01/the-zungeon-manifesto-demystifying-dungeon-creation/">The Zungeon Manifesto</a>: This is the one that finally motivated me to polish up and publish this blog post that has been in my drafts for over a year. If you want to try and make a zine - in the sense of something unpolished and unconstrained - here's a good place to start.</p> <p><a href="https://www.prismaticwasteland.com/blog/2025-is-the-year-of-the-beta">The Year of the Beta</a> - Put out something you've done this year that isn't finished. For me, I'll do one or more of these things - a set of rules for stanalone community and character relatinships I've been working on for over a year, or maybe more elements of my implied setting, probably as blog posts.</p> <p><a href="https://200proof.games/manifesto/">1E Manifesto:</a> Put out something that's complete, but a first version. Finish something instead of making something perfect.</p> <p><a href="https://symbolic.city/misc/indie-ttrpg-scene-agenda">Indie TTRPG Scene Agenda:</a> try and be a bit scrappier, a bit less dependent on big corporate platforms and more dependent on your peers.</p> <p><a href="https://nora.zone/manifesto.html">The website manifesto:</a> Not TTRPG related, but maybe some motivation to put together a website.</p> <p>I've probably missed some, let me know.</p> <p>Also, consider looking into non-RPG zines as well. There's a lot of cool stuff out there.</p> ]]></description>
        <category>Discourse</category>
    <pubDate>Fri, January 3 2025</pubDate>
  </item>


   <item>
    <title>A taxonomy of games </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/discourse/game_taxonomy_part_1_v_1.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h2 class="title">A game taxonomy, part 1</h2> <div class="notes"> <i>&quot;All models are wrong, some models are useful.&quot;</i> </div> <p>A million people have already done this - I'm kind of assuming you have vaguely absorbed the existing Internet discussions, and are familiar with terms like OSR, Story Games, etc. If you haven't, run away now and save yourself. But <a href="https://retiredadventurer.blogspot.com/2021/04/six-cultures-of-play.html">Six Cultures Of Play</a> is probably a prerequisite to understand what I'm talking about, or at least what I'm complaining about.</p> <p>I will try to, as much as possible, only discuss games that I have played. A lot of taxonomies seem to be written by someone who clearly likes one type of game a lot more than the others. For instance, I will not be discussing LARP because I don't have any relevant experience. I'm also not claiming that I am discussing the complete set of all games that exist, but I think I have played enough of them propose a taxonomy. If you're curious, I have an approximately complete list of games I've played or run <a href="../personal/games_ive_played">here.</a></p> <h1 class="subtitle">What is a TTRPG?</h1> <p>First we're going to have to look at everyone's other least favourite subject of conversation.</p> <p>TTRPGs have 2 or more people taking on the following 3 roles:</p> <ul> <li>A <em>player</em>, who is responsible for one or more characters who are the protagonists of the story.</li> <li>A <em>GM</em>, who is responsible for the remainder of the story, such as providing additional characters and other aspects of the environment that the main players exist in. To do so they might determine the outcome of uncertain events or interpret rules agreed upon by the table.</li> <li>An <em>author</em>, who provides additional, reusable material without being present. I'm using the term "author" for a lack of a better one, but it includes game books, blog posts, maps, drawings, or even fixed principles transmitted orally from game group to game group. These serve to facilitate or even replace GMing, as well as to introduce new ideas to the table without someone being physically present.</li> </ul> <p>The same person often takes on different roles at different times, sometimes in the same game.</p> <p>If you have only one of these roles, you are probably writing a book, doing improv, or some other activity. Which is of course totally fine.</p> <p>This isn't the only definion you could come up with, but I think most people would agree it isn't totally wrong, and it's a lens that I'll be using to discuss the game taxonomy.</p> <h1 class="subtitle">The actual taxonomy</h1> <img class="blog-image-heading" src="./images/taxonomy.jpg" alt="Alt text: A diagram consisting of a circle with “maximalist”, “structured narrative”, “prompt oriented” and “adventure and exploration” in a circle, with a line connecting “adventure and exploration” and “structured narrative” There is other text saying “N-dimensional space projected onto a 2D plane” “Maximalist” has “D&D 5E”, “13th age” and “Trad” next to it. Adventure and exploration has “Retroclones” and “OSR” closer to the Maximalist side, and NSR, Cairn and 20XX closer to the prompt oriented side. “Structured narrative” has FitD (near maximalist), PbtA and 10 candles (near prompt-oriented). “Prompt oriented”has “for the queen” near “structed narrative”, I’m sorry did you say street magic in the middle, and wanderhome near adventure and exploration. The words “story games” have arrows going to “prompt oriented” and “structured narrative” " /> <p>In this blog post, I'll talk about 4 categories at a high level, and how they relate to each other. In a follow up blog post, if I ever finish it, I'll break them down into subcategories, many with a lot of overlap.</p> <h1 class="subsubtitle">Maximalist Games</h1> <p>Apparently "maximalist" means something specific in art but I am not educated in such things and might be using the word wrong.</p> <p>Characteristics of a maximalist game:</p> <ul> <li><b>The three roles:</b> clearly present and distinct, with the GM and author each taking on a large responsibility for the game experience.</li> <li><b>Modularity:</b> Semi-modular: There is a main game system which is designed to be extended by other modules, but these modules cannot be used with other games easily. A game book is typically not a self-contained experience and games are usually open-ended in duration.</li> <li><b>Rules:</b> A lengthy, complex ruleset with subsystems for resolving different parts of the game that are likely to come up, primarily oriented around the success or failure of an action and its consequences.</li> <li><b>Characters:</b> The complex game mechanics provide an opportunity for players to develop a distinct character before playing them, defined by game mechanics. Character and player motivations are usually aligned.</li> <li><b>Narrative structure:</b> Campaigns usually follow conventional narrative structure, but this is driven primarily by the GM, or by adventure modules, which define an outline of the narrative.</li> <li><b>Who makes them:</b> Often require more resources to create and thus are made by corporations, but that is changing.</li> <li><b>Relationship to other media:</b> While often inspired by fantasy novels, their larger budget and longer history has allowed some of them to develop their own genre conventions distinct from other media, and in some cases have inspired movies and books.</li> <li><b>Solo games:</b> Rare, due to the prominent role of the GM.</li> </ul> <p>&quot;Trad&quot; games are a subset of these but a) I hate that word and b) I think the genre, starting especially with 4E and other inspired games, have gone in some very different directions.  It roughly corresponds to &quot;Fight D&amp;D&quot; in the Between Two Cairns taxonomy, but some games in this category involve no fighting at all.</p> <h1 class="subsubtitle">Narrative Mechanics Games</h1> <ul> <li><b>The three roles:</b> Blur the lines between GM and player more freely.</li> <li><b>Modularity:</b> Usually not very. Each game is made to create a specific experience, and the blurring of GM and player roles makes adding external content more complicated.</li> <li><b>Rules:</b> Focused on resolving problems in the context of narrative structures. Rules may facilitate pacing, allow for storytelling outside of linear time, allow players to temporarily take on a GM-like role, and allow for players to work together to create conflict between their characters.</li> <li><b>Characters:</b> Mechanics facilitate creating characters according to genre conventions with defined relationships to other characters and to NPCs. Player and character motivations are often not aligned.</li> <li><b>Narrative structure:</b> Rules are designed to support conventional narrative structures and genre conventions.</li> <li><b>Who makes them:</b> The focused scope of these games mean that they are often made by individuals rather than corporations, but there is a trend towards some of them being made by mid-sized organizations. Long development cycles may be needed to provide a polished experience, leading to some amount of professionalization.</li> <li><b>Relationship to other media:</b> Usually strongly inspired by other media, allowing you to create stories similar to movies, books, TV shows, etc.</li> <li><b>Solo games:</b> Rare, with Ironsworn as a notable exception.</li> </ul> <p>Some &quot;story games&quot; fall into this, but I think &quot;story games&quot; has split into two meaningfully distinct categories. I've met enough people who only like one of the two categories. I think they are perceived as more similar than they are because there's less internet drama about the difference between them.</p> <h1 class="subsubtitle">Prompt-based storytelling</h1> <ul> <li><b>The three roles:</b> Blur the lines between the GM, player and author, with the GM often being absent.</li> <li><b>Modularity:</b> Usually self-contained experiences with limited modularity.</li> <li><b>Rules:</b> Often entirely forego mechanics for failure or success; mechanics tend to be minimal and about making suggestions regarding the story to tell, with the written text sometimes acting primarily as a GM or even player who is not present.</li> <li><b>Characters:</b>  Character creation is usually a minor to nonexistent part of the game, with characters being defined by decisions made at the table. In some cases, all characters are already predefined. Characters are usually defined in words rather than numbers. Player and character motivations are rarely aligned.</li> <li><b>Narrative structure:</b> Stories often forego conventional narrative structures, and are focused around exploring relationships, ideas, or experiences. If a narrative structure is defined, it is usually in the form of a defined endpoint, with the purpose of the game being to explore how the characters get there.</li> <li><b>Who makes them:</b> Leans heavily towards DIY or single creators. Often comes in formats other than books.</li> <li><b>Relationship to other media:</b> Inspiration comes less from established genres and more from life experiences. Genre fiction is less likely to be an inspiration.</li> <li><b>Solo games:</b> Very common, due to the reduced role of the GM.</li> </ul> <h1 class="subsubtitle">Adventure/exploration games</h1> <ul> <li><b>The three roles:</b> Blur the lines between GM and author, both at the table and culturally.</li> <li><b>Modularity:</b> Are highly modular: not only are supplements and adventures often interchangeable, but are often not tied to specific systems.</li> <li><b>Rules:</b> Have relatively short rulesets focused on generating situations (on the GM side) and resolving danger (on the player side).</li> <li><b>Characters:</b> Characters are mostly created organically in play through interactions with the environment, including the tools at their disposal. Random generation is common. Character and player motivations are usually aligned.</li> <li><b>Narrative structure:</b> Campaigns often do not follow a typical narrative structure, aside from perhaps an escalation in danger, scope and/or strangeness. </li> <li><b>Who makes them:</b> Their modular nature means that they are often created in a DIY manner, through zines, blog posts, and informal discussions, though mid-size companies are also prevalent.</li> <li><b>Relationship to other media:</b> Inspiration from other media is often mostly vibes-based, with genre fiction, folklore, and even musical genres and political movements (for better or worse) being prominent. It doesn't seek to emulate the characters or narrative structure of other genres.</li> <li><b>Solo games:</b> Relatively common, usually provided by an additional module that may be specific and general-purpose, often focused on a GM emulator known as an "oracle."</li> </ul> <p>&quot;OSR&quot; games are a subset of these, but a good number of these also make many OSR people very angry. It roughly corresponds to &quot;Door D&amp;D&quot;, but dungeon crawling is not inherent to this genre.</p> <h1 class="subsubtitle">Other ways of looking at these categories</h1> <p>You could also map these on axes:</p> <ul> <li>distinct GM/player/writer role vs combined roles: maximalist vs prompt-based at opposite ends of this spectrum</li> <li>Highly self-contained vs highly modular: narrative vs adventure/exploration</li> <li>Strong genre conventions vs naturalistic approach: maximalist/narrative vs adventure/exploration/prompt based</li> <li>Resembles a D&amp;D vs does not really resemble a D&amp;D: maximalist/adventure/exploration vs narrative/prompt based</li> <li>for symmetry I want to put another axis for maximalist/prompt based but I can't think of anything they have in common. Oh well.</li> </ul> <p>But I also don't think this is a complete enumeration of all possible types of games either - this is some kind of n-dimensional space that has only 4 blobs on it</p> <h2 class="subtitle">The part of the taxonomy blog post where you realize this is actually just me going on about my own preferences this entire time</h2> <p>I've played and enjoyed all 4 types of games, but putting this together has helped me figure something out - why it is that I like both the NSR side of OSR games and like the &quot;super weird&quot; story games. And why I don't seem to be the only one, even though these are often talked about as opposites. Because if you split story games into two genres, the similarities between prompt-based games and adventure/exploration games comes out. </p> <h1 class="subtitle">Previous posts</h1> <p>I made a <a href="osr_and_story_games.html"> previous post</a> arguing there's a lot of overlap between modern trends in some OSR games and in some story games, here: I realize now I was actually describing the section between adventure/exploration games and prompt based games. It all makes sense with the circle.</p> <p>I have <a href="door_dnd.html"> another post</a> where I discuss the overlap specifically from the perspective of solo games.</p> <p>I attempted to come up with my own definition for NSR  <a href="what_is_nsr.html">here.</a></p> ]]></description>
    <category>Discourse</category>
    <pubDate>Fri, December 13 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

   <item>
    <title>Vampires (and the afterlife, and undead) </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/wip/vampires.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>This was originally supposed to be for Vampire Week which was like a month ago. I wrote most of this then but never actually published it. Also, as you can see, I got way off course on the way to talking about vampires, so that only the last third actually has anything to do with vampires.</p> <h3 class="subtitle">First, how does the afterlife work</h3> <p>These days most of my writing has a vague, implied setting, but one thing I have not defined is the afterlife. The afterlife is generally something of a problem. For instance, in Baldur's Gate 3, it has been pointed out that the Forgotten Realms having a well-defined afterlife has all sorts of weird implciations on characters' motivations, especially Hell being a literal, real place you can go look at. A lot of character motivations then seem incongruous with the world as presented. On the other hand, fantasy adventures tend to assume there is some form of existence after death, at least so you can like ask questions of the dead. Maybe even bring the dead back (though I want that to be fairly limited).</p> <p> The solution I settled on is a kind of Sabriel situation (though not dangerous to the dead). There is a liminal space between life and death that the living can sometimes carefully delve into, and sometimes the dead can influence the world of the living, as ghosts. The spirits of the dead may hang around for a while, so long as they are concerned with the affairs of the living. But as their ties to the world of the living fade, most will pass on to whatever comes next. The liminal realm is a rather dreary shadow of the world of the living, liminal not in a cool or atmospheric way but in the way an airport is. As you travel deeper into the land of the dead, there is no returning at a certain point, either for the dead or for the trespassing living.</p> <p>In some cultures, it's common to stay around for some time to help your descendents, though that help is only subtle and indirect. To encourage this, the living can give gifts to the dead, of the things they enjoyed in life. Where this is common, the land between life and death is more interesting, sometimes even having entire cities. These cities, however, have something of the atmosphere of Vegas - constructed entirely for the purpose of entertainment, as boredom is the only real problem; a strange facsimile of the real world; and surrounded by an endless wasteland on all sides.</p> <p>In other cultures, you're expected to move on fairly quickly and leave life to the living, just as the living are expected to move through the various phases of life. Specific individuals do stick around for their own purposes, if they have unfinished business, and meddle in the world of the living as a ghost, but they most often would be motivated by spite, vengeance, jealousy, and so on.</p> <h3 class="subtitle">Necromancy and the undead</h3> <p>I want necromancy to be feared and somewhat taboo, but I want to give a reason other than "because we said so".</p> <p>The land of the dead is dangerous to the living, but not to the already dead - the monsters that lurk here need the life essence of the living to manifest in the real world, in the form of mortal blood, as well as a vessel to inhabit, most easily made from something that was once living. They also seem to desire mortal blood for its own sake. And so necromancers can use blood d (themselves or others') to bargain with these beings.</p> <p>When given the opportunity to manifest in the physical realm, these beings can only have the nature of the blood they were fed in the ritual that awakens them. For instance, a being created from a rat has only the understanding of a rat, clever and able to fight but unable to talk or reason like a human. Some of the more desperate undead may be satisified with this bargain, and a skeleton animated by such a force may be useful to a necromancer. A necromancer can give some of their own blood to bring forth the intelligent undead for a short amount of time, but to create something truly powerful a human sacrifice is needed. As part of this bargain, these beings will usually be asked to swear a binding oath to obey the necromancer, but there are many ways to twist the words of those oaths.</p> <p>Once in the land of the living, eventually they will exhaust their supply of blood and be forced to return. The only way to remain is by consuming more blood, and they prefer human blood, although without ritual assistance human blood does not make them more powerful. They can also conserve their energy indefinitely by waiting without moving, and so an ancient tomb undisturbed for centuries might contain skeletons that will come to life when disturbed.</p> <p>Necromancy isn't strictly evil, but at best it's very dangerous. You might, for instance, empower the skeleton of an animal (to avoid grave robbing) with an animal sacrifice, which is no different from eating meat, really, but there's always a danger that it attacks someone. It's also unclear <em>why</em> the creatures of the Beyond are so desperate to enter the mortal world, but some believe that there is some vast and organized plan, and every undead incursion brings this plan closer to fruition. </p> <p>You can also make other deals with the strange powers of the beyond, such as to bargain for knowledge or strange powers in exchange for a smaller offering of blood, but any power of the Beyond worth bargaining on is powerful enough that it may find a way to slip into the world of mortals - either by finding the dead body of an animal nearby that you overlooked, or possibly even by possessing your body.</p> <h3 class="subtitle">Finally, vampires</h3> <div class="notes"> <p>I have <a href="./types_of_people_cairn.html">a set of these sorts of templates</a> to apply to Cairn characters. It could maybe be grafted onto other systems that are roll under? </p> <p>I decided to double-subvert this by making vampires evil again - going specifically for the version where people become vampires after being dead instead of being turned. </p> <p>This is also quite a bit more powerful than the other ones I made - this is probably only suitable for a solo game, or maybe as an antagonist. If you played them as a villain in your game, I think it should not be too obvious at first that they're a vampire - until they come back from the dead- and then the players need to figure out what to do so they don't have to keep fighting them.</p> </div> <p> You, once an ordinary human, have committed deeds in life so vile and unholy that upon death, your soul cannot pass on to wherever it is that souls go after death. Instead, 2d4 days later, you awake in your grave and, no longer needing to breathe, you claw your way to the surface. </p> <p>You aren't "inherently" evil, in the sense that you still have free will, and you can turn your back on your previous misdeeds, though it becomes more challenging due to your vampiric nature. You can in theory stop drinking blood: you have the option to change your ways, you just are unlikely to do so given you ended up in this position to begin with. Nor are you likely to see any reward for doing so in this life, and the gates to the next one are permantly closed. Still, however, if you manage to avoid being destroyed through the centuries, that is a long time, and you may find yourself changing your ways.</p> <ul> <li><b>Boon:</b> Whenever you die, an unholy power knits your body back together and come back to life in 3 days with 1d6 Strength. This costs an equivalent amount of Doom. If there are significant barriers to your body coming back together, this isn't possible - for instance, you have been beheaded with your head buried separately, a stake has been firmly driven into your heart, or your body has been significantly burnt or dismembered. </li> <li><b>Boon:</b> If you drink the blood of a living human (or similar), you drain 1d6 from their WIL save and may restore the same number of points to any of your saves other than Doom. This is the only way you can heal. You otherwise do not need to eat, drink or breathe. If your victim reaches 0 WIL they act as if permanently charmed.</li> <li><b>Boon:</b> You have three of the following spells.</li> (1) Beast Form (must be a creature of the night), (2) Command, (3) Charm, (4) Control Weather, (5) Haste, (6) Hypnotize, (7) Manse,  (8) Smoke Form, (9) Snuff <li><b>Bane:</b> You cannot abide the taste and smell of the food of mortals, and the stronger the smell the more it repels you. Garlic and spices in particular are anathema to you - they smell overwhelmingly vile. </li> <li><b>Bane:</b> You cannot enter a consecrated place, or approach a holy symbol, unless permitted by the god of that place. Likewise, you cannot enter a home unless invited in.</li> <li><b>Your fate:</b> When <i>Doom</i> reaches zero, you can no longer hide that you are a corpse, and you must either flee into the wilderness or face a certain second death.</li> </ul>]]>
    </description>
    <category>WIP</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, November 24 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

   <item>
    <title>Big Bad Con 2024 </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/personal/big_bad_con_2024.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[<p>Big bad con now feels like about a million years ago, though it was almost exactly a month since writing this.</p> <p>It's the only game convention I go to - largely because it's local and I try to avoid flying these days - but it's a pretty good one. A lot of the games are a bit outside of the usual set of games I play, which I appreciate. It's a chance to play things I probably won't play for the rest of the year, and I try and push myself to try new things and, in particular, to play games I've never played before.  So this post is mostly actually going to be a discussion of the games I played, in chronological order.</p> <p>I played 8 games. My top 3 were City of Winter, Trophy Dark and Shinobigami in that order; of the playtest games I am especially excited by the potential of Gnostisystem.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Games on demand part 1</h2> <p>I played two 2-hour games, both playtests. One was a Starfinder adventure called Absalom Station Animal Control, about trying to catch escaped cats, where you can't hurt the cats but the cats can hurt you. It was one of the better examples I'd seen of trying to play a game without violence but using all of the mechanics of a &quot;trad&quot; RPG (I dislike the term &quot;trad&quot; in this context but I guess we're stuck with it.) It's not usually my first choice of genre but I had fun. It used a grid-based, initiative-based tactical game system to not kill things, and the increasingly difficult cats are easy to play as funny and cute. It was my first time playing Starfinder, my second time playing a Pathfinder-family game. It was also my second time playing a social media influencer in a sci fi game.</p> <p>As a side note I'd like to see a wider range of tones in sci fi games, especially for more lightweight game systems. I feel like sci fi tends to be pretty grim, which is fun sometimes, but I think we could use more lightweight space shenanigans games as well.</p> <p>Next was a playtest of a GM-less game called A Reason To Be about people in a society that is generally pretty good trying to solve minor problems in their lives. The game had an index card based system where you shuffled and drew index cards and each time the same index card came up you progressed your character's story arc a bit more. You also collaboratively create the community, which I enjoyed. It's a nice game for telling a quick and self-contained story. Though after playing through it I feel like I would do a much better job of playing it a second time.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">OD&amp;D and Jennell Jaquays</h2> <p>This was my first time playing OD&amp;D. Despite doing a lot of stuff on kind of the &quot;NSR&quot; side of things, I have very little experience playing actual retroclones, although I had played modern rewritings of some classic adventures (White Plume Mountain in particular). We actually played the Fantastic Medieval Campaigns version.</p> <p>In a lot of ways we played this in what I imagine was a relatively traditional way. We even had a shot-caller, though the way it was implemented actually made a lot more sense than how I heard people sometimes used it - the position was rotated every half-hour, and their responsibility was just to make a final decision after we'd all talked about what to do next.</p> <p>In many ways it felt surprisingly modern, though. The game was not incredibly deadly (one person died during the final confrontation) and mostly felt pretty fair. We had meaningful choices to make, solved most problems without violence, a lot of the encounters were primarily social, and just exploring the dungeon and piecing together what was going on was a lot of fun. It felt more like a modern &quot;NSR&quot; game than how I imagined actual old school games to be. I wouldn't play this type of game every time, but I'd definitely enjoy playing it now and again.</p> <p>I have generally been aware that early D&amp;D was in fact played in a lot of different ways, not just what people think of as OSR. This game left me curious about whether there is a notable difference in, say, adventures descended from Gygax's work vs Jaquays'.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Trophy Dark</h2> <p>Finally, got to play Trophy Dark! I'd previously tried and failed during Games On Demand.</p> <p>The game was set in a convent in Northern California shortly after Vatican 2. The premise is that we are all new nuns heading to the convent, where strange things are happening - strange creatures seen in the woods, followed by a mysterious illness.</p> <p>I'm not sure how typical a Trophy Dark game it was. While we were all doomed from fairly early on, we managed to have what I think was a rather touching story under tragic circumstances, choosing to defy the lovecraftinan Dog-Man despite certain death. We also I think were all a bit too cautious and so our Ruin never got all that high. I also think we had a really good group for this - I thought everyone played their characters in a really compelling way.</p> <p>I played a down-to-earth daughter of a farmer who insisted for as long as possible that there was a reasonable explanation for everything going on. Unfortunately I didn't manage to incorporate my secret lesbian past until the epilogue.</p> <p>(I ended up going to a panel later about playing games set in the real world - I think it would have helped me play with more confidence if I knew more about Catholicism.)</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Apparatchik</h2> <p>This was another playtest of what turned out to be a kind of interesting take on a &quot;trad&quot; game. Unfortunately at least one of the players was hoping for something a lot more in the realm of story games and was clearly not having a good time throughout.</p> <p>But I thought it was pretty interesting - you play as bureaucrats assigning resources according to rules in an almost board-game-like way. In a sense this is to worker placement boardgames as D&amp;D is to tactical miniature wargames. But it quickly becomes apparent that it is not actually possible to win. You don't have enough resources to save everyone, and the best you can do is mitigate the damage. Another point of frustration I think was that it wasn't clear to all the players that there was no way to win and they thought they were just playing badly or misunderstanding the rules. If you don't like complicated board games you probably wouldn't like this game.</p> <p>You create characters that are in over their heads and assigned to this problem more or less due to losing some political battle. I played a naive and ambitious young bureaucrat who didn't realize that being appointed as the head of the committee by the others was not in fact doing me a favour. Like a lot of &quot;trad&quot; style games, the RP aspect is mostly improv and the rules are mostly around the mechanics of problem solving. This is the main thing which some of the players bounced off of - I actually don't mind &quot;trad&quot; games, I've mostly moved away from them due to being dissatisfied with the actual combat mechanics of the ones that are popular now. I think this would be a great game for players who mostly play D&amp;D 5E or Pathfinder who want to branch out a bit, but not too much.</p> <p>I feel like this is a game I'd have fun running, for the right group.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Panel: Playing Games in the Real World</h2> <p>This is the only panel I went to, it was a pretty good one. Some notes I took:</p> <ul> <li>A setting as your personal ethnography of a city</li> <li>A setting in the real world as your research of something you're interested in (including in the past)</li> <li>A setting in the real world about capturing a specific vibe</li> <li>A fantasy or folkloric setting that looks for the magic in the real world</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Players may automatically have familiarity with real-world settings. This both can be good and can be bad (if you have different perspectives)</li> <li>Real world history: watch out for anachronisms e.g. cell phones. But also be flexible (e.g. allow for player diversity)</li> <li>Instead of building from the ground up, you have to consider each element and whether or not to exclude it</li> <li>Can be easier to get players emotionally invested</li> <li>Easy to visualise, may have more resources to do so (e.g. Google Maps). It can be fun to play in a place and then later visit it IRL</li> </ul> <ul> <li>It is harder to populate a place that you don't have real-world familiarity with, especially if you want to be respectful.</li> <li>Actual real-world conflicts rooted in systemic oppression can come up. You may want to explore this, or it could be off-putting to people affected by it. And it can also be off-putting to have it be notably absent.</li> <li>Rather than avoid entire subjects, be able to recover from and grow from mistakes gracefully.</li> <li>Your responsibilities in a public game are higher than in a private game.</li> </ul> <h2 class="subtitle">Small Press Vending</h2> <p>This went pretty well. I mostly sold Procedures to Discover the Path Ahead, I was a little disappointed that Friends, Liars and Troublemakers didn't sell that well, but I realized that actually maybe a zine full of stat-less NPCs is actually one of the more OSR-coded things that I sell, in a weird way. There were several people who had heard of Cairn and someone even bought my last Murky Bog pamphlet. Given that this convention is not totally the target audience for the games I make, I was pretty happy.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">City of Winter</h2> <p>I got lucky with this one, there was a last-minute cancellation and I managed to swoop in.</p> <p>I really liked this game and I want to imagine myself having the ability to do a long campaign of it. Unfortunately my current story game type group just established that the group as a whole doesn't like GM-less games, and also I feel like this is a game to be played IRL. It is such a gorgeous game.</p> <p>It's about an extended family going on a long journey from their home because something terrible is happening. They have cards that represent their culture, and as they travel, they pick up cards from other cultures and may adopt those. It's a really good representation, I think, of the immigrant experience, as someone who myself has a mixed hand of cards.</p> <p>Each culture is roughly represented by an animal, and the cards did a really good job of being interesting and ambiguous, and of creating areas both for conflict and for cultural exchange as we encountered different cultures. The structure of having a family that grows older over time was also really good - we had a lot of really touching moments throughout the game. Playing members of an intergenerational family (which also is growing older over time) was pretty cool, especially given that RPG games are more likely to be about a group of friends who are peers.</p> <p>There were two kids where it started out with one bullying the other, where with some help from the adults they ended up good friends and later, adoptive siblings. There was a romance between two characters who just happened to be traveling together at the start but later formally joined the family. I played a grandmother type who tried to keep everyone happy while protecting our traditions - there was an extended running joke of getting the more rowdy kid to carry on traditions involving loud and annoying musical instruments.</p> <p>Also if I had a dollar for every time I played a game where it was ambiguous whether we are actual birds or metaphorical birds and we realized we were not on the same page halfway through the game,  I would have two dollars.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Shinobigami</h2> <p>This was a Games on Demand game. This is a highly PvP story game where we play members of different ninja clans, scheming to end up with the McGuffin at the end.</p> <p>It had some interesting mechanics - a grid of combat skills where you have some trained skills but can use other skills with a difficulty depending on how far it is from a trained skill, and a health system which wipes out columns of skills. Combat is heavily based around an initiative system which also determines your distance from each other as well as the actions you can take and effectively your HP, and involves secretly choosing an initiative, and was surprisingly tactical.</p> <p>You also have an ultimate attack with a very long name which you of course have to dramatically say to activate. I really enjoyed getting to have over-the-top monologues as well. </p> <p>But mostly the game was about relationships between the characters and trying to figure out each other's secrets. Everyone had a secret goal as well. There were a lot of great dramatic reveals and a satisfying ending.</p> <p>I played a sneaky rogue who had rejected all ninja clans, and I started with the McGuffin, which I managed to hold onto until the very end when I was finally defeated. I had a tragic friendship with an opponent who I was also required to defeat as my secret goal. Despite being a very PvP game, I feel like we were also working together to generate drama and tragedy. This is a case where I can't tell if the game was really good or I just ended up with a really good set of players (or both).</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Gnostisystem</h2> <p>I was going to do a LARP, which was then going to be Yazeba's B&amp;B, and after both were cancelled I went back to Games On Demand.</p> <p>It's very much still in development and I'm very excited about its potential.</p> <p>It's a &quot;trad&quot; game where you draw an esoteric diagram according to some rules and that determines how combat works. So your character sheet is a cool drawing, made up of circles of three colours and connections between them. The colours correspond to attacks, defences and movement, and the lines between them allow you to have actions do more than one type of thing.</p> <p>You fight other esoteric diagrams. The rules for the diagrams are pretty simple but have a surprising amount of depth to them. When we got to the final &quot;boss fight&quot; it was legitimately quite hard and we had to really think through the tactics of defeating it. It's also very satisfying to come up with interesting combinations and have those work out in a battle. It was the most engaged I had been in tactical combat in a game in quite a long time, and it has a  much simpler set of rules than most other tactical combat oriented games, given the amount of emergent complexity in those rules.</p> <p>It's about going to a strange spiritual realm and fighting strange entities to fuel some kind of religious obsession. Damage goes directly to your identity and sense of self and you heal yourself by picking up parts of these strange entities and grafting them to your soul. It's a dungeon crawler.</p> <p>I'm hoping for more focus on polishing the out of combat stuff in the future - I think this entire concept has a ton of potential that is not totally yet realized. In particular, the implications on identity and character growth, as well as what exactly the nature of the spiritual entities you are fighting is, or what your end goal might be, could be fleshed out more.  But if the author doesn't go that direction I could see myself just hacking the game a lot and making it into what I want it to be. I'm also hoping for a high-budget kickstarter with a lot of art, like usually I feel we have too many of these, but this is a concept that deserves cool art. I think overall this is my favourite take on a &quot;trad&quot; game in a long time. It's also totally unlike any other game I've seen.</p> <h2 class="subtitle">Is it a good idea to play 8 games in one weekend</h2> <p>Usually, it is advised that you do the exact opposite of this. I was very tired afterwards. In between games I had zero social energy at all. But this is also for me my main opportunity to play many of these types of games. I also don't know a huge number of people in this particular scene and the ones I know I don't know that well, the rest of the year I'm mostly in a different corner of the TTRPG world, and in the past attempts to "network" mostly made me feel bad.  If you're trying to grow a career, spending an entire convention playing games 12 hours a day is probably not the way to go, but for me it's worth it.</p> <p>Half of the games I played were Games On Demand. A great thing about Games On Demand is you can ascertain your energy levels like 5 minutes before the games start.</p>]]></description>
    <category>WIP, Worldbuilding</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, November 23 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

   <item>
    <title>The Most Important Two Pages of Procedures to Discover the Path Ahead </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/extras/ptdtpa_preview.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[ <h1 class="title">The Most Important Two Pages of Procedures to Discover the Path Ahead</h1> <p>I've decided to publish a blog version of the main idea in Procedures to Discover the Path Ahead because I keep wanting to tell people that I wrote something that solves their problem, but I don't want to seem spammy and ask them to buy something.</p> <p>So here is the core mechanic. You have a counter that goes from 0 to 6 and you add the results of a d6 to the counter. You then look up the result in a table. This is basically a depth crawl.</p> <ol> <li>Water</li> <li>Farmland/village</li> <li>Waystation (e.g. an inn, monastery, friendly military post, roadside stalls). Add 1 to the counter.</li> <li>Gentle wilds (rolling hills, meadows, forests that are well explored and used by loggers, hunters, etc). Add 1 to the counter.</li> <li>Farmland/village, again. Add 1 to the counter.</li> <li>Rough wilds (bogs, scary forests, rocky hills, small mountains). Add 2 to the counter.</li> <li>Barrier (Deserts, oceans, mountains). Place up to 2 spaces away and add 2 to the counter when you reach that spot. Have it extend a few spaces in either direction.</li> <li>Unfriendly (monsters, bandits, army of a rival kingdom). Add 1 to the counter.</li> <li>Rough wilds again. Add 1 to the counter.</li> <li>Town, placed 2 spaces away. Reset the counter to 0.</li> <li>Deep wilds: enter the land of the fey, etc.</li> <li>City. Place 3 spaces away and set the counter to 0.</li> </ol> <h1 class="subtitle">Example of a journey</h1> <p>A space can be a hex, a day's travel, an hour's travel, etc.  If you're doing this without a map, I usually roll 2 options and have the option of going one of two ways at each point. For example:</p> <div class="notes"> <p>(Counter 0, roll a 5 and 1) (<strong>farmland</strong>, water) You set off on your journey with the ocean on one side and a seaside village on the other, the road leading through little gardens and orchards. You head through the village. +1</p> <p>(counter 1, you roll a 1 and a 2) (farmland, <strong>waystation</strong>) The path continues into a valley with more villages, but you decide to take a road that will lead you farther afield. You stop for the night in an inn. +1</p> <p>(counter 2, you roll a 5 and a 3) (<strong>barrier</strong>, farmland) The road continues up towards a steep and foreboding mountain range. One fork takes you by some pastoral villages at the foot of the mountains, but you are going on a Journey. You set off to climb through a narrow and treacherous mountain pass. +2</p> <p>(counter 4, 1, 4) (<strong>farmland</strong>, unfriendly) You make it through, exhausted, and see an imposing fort ahead, flying a flag with a skull on it. You instead take refuge in a mountainside village. The food is plain but hearty and you manage to regain your strength. +1</p> <p>(counter 5, 6, 10) (deep wilds, <strong>town</strong>) Before you leave, the villagers point out to you two immense stones in the side of one of the mountains. They tell you that those who pass through often do not return, that it is the gate to some other world. You decide ths sounds like a bad idea. You can see what looks like a town further down in the valley, and decide to head there instead.</p> <p>(counter reset to 0, 6, 3) (rough wilds, <strong>waystation</strong>) The trail does head through a particularly ominous forest, but the villagers tell you that if you stay on the main path and head for the monastery you should be fine. The forest, they tell you, is full of wolves, but they keep off the main path. You follow their advice and reach a monastery, where you spend the night and learn more about the area. It is ruled, they say, by a cruel tyrant (in the castle), but whose grasp on power is fragile. The town is technically under their control, but largely independent.</p> <p>(counter 1 but you've reached the town) You reach the town! We'll end our journey here but we could also set off in a new direction, or return to one of the interesting and dangerous locations you passed up before.</p> </div> <p>I have tables in the book to flesh out each location a bit more, but you could equally well use similar tables in other books. You could use this in conjunction with other game rules: add random encounters, for instance.</p> <p>The goal is to randomly create a map or a journey which also follows a satisfying narrative pattern. Stateless random location generators end up feeling a bit incoherent sometimes, since anything can appear next to anything else. By adding some state, the journey naturally follows a narrative, where it increases in difficulty as you get farther from home, requiring you to reach several obstacles, before reaching your goal. It also feels more naturalistic, with areas near major settlements having smaller settlements and relatively safe areas, and more remote areas being more dangerous. It also means that potential adventure sites  (the portal to a strange world, the mountains, the ominous castle), require some effort to discover.</p> <h1 class="subtitle">Example of a hex map</h1> <p>You can also do this with a hex map. In this case, write the counter number on each hex. When you go to a new hex, take the average of the hexes next to it that you've visted.  You can also pre-seed the map with ocean hexes (e.g. have it be around a bay, or a peninsual like Scandinavia) and it works out pretty well.</p> <p>I mean to eventually have a page walking through an example of making a hex map, but it would make this blog post really long so it's coming later. Here are two maps that I made using this, though:</p> <img class="blog-image-heading" src="./images/map_forest.png" alt="A map of a region with water in two opposite corners, a temple on a plateau and a town to the north, another town to the south, forest to the west and desert to the east." /> <img class="blog-image-heading" src="./images/map-mountains.png" alt="A map showing a mountainous region, with a large city next to a plateau in the north, forest in the middle, a valley to the south with a monastery, water to the west and a town next to the water." /> <h1 class="subtitle">Using this structure for other things</h1> <p>I have some other types of overland journey in the book. One thing I've been meaning to explore, but haven't until now, is using it to generate dungeons. Here's a first attempt:</p> <ol> <li>A temple or other external-facing structure</li> <li>A sealed door +3</li> <li>An incursion from the natural world</li> <li>A minor enemy, guarding a useful item +1</li> <li>A secret revealed or a useful item +1</li> <li>An obvious trap or puzzle +2</li> <li>A passage heading downwards. +3</li> <li>Another entrance. If the dungeon continues, reset counter to 0</li> <li>A powerful enemy +1</li> <li>A sealed door +2</li> <li>An ancient evil unleashed +1</li> <li>A great treasure</li> </ol> <p>On a 6, the dungeon loops back on itself.</p> <p>I tried it out and it makes some decent small dungeons. It currently has no guidance on exits for rooms, I'm just doing what feels right in the moment, but if I made this into something publishable I would probably want to come up with a procedure for that, as well as more guidance for how to actually stock the rooms. I also might want to tweak it to make bigger dungeons. But as a first, off the cuff implementation without any effort spent refining it, I'm pretty happy with it. There are multiple paths and a sense of progress as you go deeper.</p> <img class="blog-image-heading" src="./images/ptdtpa_dungeon.png" alt="A dungeon with a temple, one route that leads to a trap and treasure, another that leads to a monster and then a treasure room beyond as well as sealed ancient evil, and another side route that just has a major monster as well as another entrance." /> <p>(Made with Dungeon Scrawl)</p> <p>Here's a slightly weirder one that I did, that I'm not going to try doing on an actual map. I like that it ended up being very vertical. Also this is the point where I decided we needed another sealed door farther down. It's still super short though - you basically have one choice to make - do you try and fight Big Scary Monster, maybe with the help of Lore, or do you fight the slightly less scary monster and then deal with the door? Or maybe3 the Big Scary Monster leaves to go to the lake sometimes.</p> <img class="blog-image-heading" src="./images/ptdtpa_dungeon_vertical.jpg" alt="A rough sketch of a dungeon. It's surrounded by an underground lake, branches into 'temple' and 'lore' rooms, has a large monster guarding treasure, and a smaller monster with a different route to the treasure" /> <p>If I was playing solo, I'd probably make the room with &quot;lore&quot; be basically a token for something I can then retroactively say applied to the situation.</p> <h1 class="subtitle">General design considerations when writing your own</h1> <ul> <li>The more frequent you increment the counter, the faster it goes.</li> <li>Anything 1-6 can happen on the first roll.</li> <li>Consider things within 6 of each other. Does it make sense for them to occur back to back?.</li> <li>Things in the 3-9 range or so will show up more often.</li> </ul> <p>I don't have a license for this "system" because I think 90% of it isn't copyrightable anyway, aside from the exact wording that I use, and I think there is a tendency for people to over-claim what is copyrightable in the RPG world. I'm happy for you to make use of this or to make your own versions of these tables, and I'd love to hear about it if you do.</p> ]]></description>
    <category>Playable</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, November 16 2024</pubDate>
  </item>


      <item>
    <title>Two Western Solo Games: Tarnation and God's Gonna Cut You Down </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/actualplay/tarnation_ggcyd.html</link>
    <description> <![CDATA[<h2 class="title">Tarnation and God's Going To Cut You Down</h2><h1 class="subtitle">Intro</h1> <p>I recently playtested Tarnation, although unfortunately I never finished the game because I lost the index card I was using. Maybe it'll turn up and then I'll finish it. I then played God's Going To Cut You Down, and realized they are both kind of Western-y games. They're quite different - Tarnation is definitely Weird, and GGCYD is pretty normal. Tarnation guides you through a kind of clock-based story structure where you should hopefully survive; in GGCYD you are doomed and you're playing to find out your downfall.</p> <p>I ended up playing pretty terrible people in both games. Also, for GGCYD maybe I leaned too hard into the tropes of the genre, I have never written anything that less passes the Bechdel test.  I don't think you have to play either character as that terrible though; in particular the example character in the GGCYD book tends to make mistakes more in the context of his religious beliefs, and his ultimate failure is a lot less serious. I don't have a Christian background (religiously or culturally), so I ended up going with someone who is morally flawed in ways I am better at understanding.  I kind of flailed around a bit before I really got my bearings on what was happening as well; Westerns aren't a genre I'm very familiar with either. (Why did I get this game, you ask? I like doomed protagonists, especially when they doomed themselves.)</p> <p>I think the Tarnation one is the best writing I've done in solo journaling so far, maybe because I was finally brave enough to do real dialogue. I am extremely not confident about my ability to write dialogue. Maybe that's why I like writing adventures, because I am making the dialogue someone else's responsibility.</p> <h1  class="subtitle">Tarnation</h1> <div class="notes"> <p><b>Emma Smith</b></p> <ul> <li>Talents: brawling, sleight of hand</li> <li>Personal effects: hidden revolver, deck of cards</li> <li>Companion: a mule named Daisy</li> <li>Cannot abide anyone else in charge</li> </ul> </div> <p>Me and Daisy heard they were looking for us, slipped out just before dawn. They expect people like me to stay up late and sleep in late, but I've always slept lightly. I heard they were asking questions about a man named Jack who'd disappeared, who had last quarreled with me over a card game.</p> <p>I considered throwing away my revolver, but thought I might need it where I was going.</p> <p>Daisy is stubborn but she knows how to walk quiet. As do I.</p> <p>I could barely see the glow of the sun over the horizon but I could tell it was going to be a hot day. The road was dusty so we kept off of it. The dry grass crunched underfoot, and we headed to the other side of the ridge line before anyone woke up.</p> <div class="notes"> <ul> <li>Quicksilver</li> <li>Breakdown</li> <li>Stake: injury</li> <li>Initial bar: 3+</li> </ul> </div> <p>I didn't want to head across the border, I never had before, but they were sure to find me on the road. What I didn't expect was that Daisy would refuse to continue. There was another donkey just into the borderlands. Like Daisy, but silvery. And Daisy was not having it.</p> <p>I'd heard of the quicksilver people. I heard that they would take strange shapes. But why take the shape of my damned mule.</p> <p>Maybe I could turn her loose and she'd walk back to town? Maybe they'd think, then, that I died in the borderlands. But I couldn't bring myself to leave her. I brought some apples with me and I use them to try and coax Daisy forward. I then have an idea. I walk up to the quicksilver donkey and offer it an apple as well.</p> <p>It took the donkey, and then it changed shape. It changed into the shape of Jack. I don't remember falling to the ground.</p> <div class="notes"> <ul> <li>Traveler</li> <li>Disappearance</li> <li>Quicksilver implement</li> <li>6+, lowered to 1+ by raising the bar</li> </ul> </div> <p>I wake up and Daisy is gone. A man is standing by me. He looks confused. &quot;Who are you, and where am I?&quot; he says. He's holding a strange device.</p> <p>&quot;Where's my mule?&quot; I reply.</p> <p>&quot;I can find them,&quot; he says, gesturing to the device, &quot;not that I've seen them. But look. I mean you no harm. Tell me where I am and I'll point you in the direction of the mule.&quot;</p> <p>Without thinking, I name the town. He frowns. &quot;I've heard of it. Collected a bounty there once, many years ago.&quot;</p> <p>&quot;You're a bounty hunter?&quot; I say, trying to sound casual.</p> <p>&quot;I suppose so. Name's Tom. I like to think of myself as more someone who tries to bring some justice to this world. Real justice, you know, not The Law.&quot;</p> <p>&quot;Name's Myrtle&quot;, I say, saying the first name that comes to mind.</p> <p>&quot;Well, I better head into town in any case. Get my bearings, get breakfast, then head back.&quot; He fiddles with some dials. &quot;What's your mule's name?&quot;</p> <p>&quot;Daisy.&quot;</p> <p>He squints. &quot;Closest thing named Daisy is uh thatwaways. Looks like she's ranged, though. Do you know how to range?&quot;</p> <p>&quot;Never done it.&quot;</p> <p>&quot;It's not safe. Maybe better to head back into town with me. There are criminals and such about too, you know.&quot;</p> <p>I realize this is my best shot, when his hands are full and he's looking down. I don't want to do it. It started with Jack and now it's going to be Tom and who knows where my life is headed now. But if Tom makes it back to town, he'll be hunting me next, and his revolvers look well-used. So I shoot while his head is down. I grab the device before it falls and crashes on the ground. For some reason, running seems right. Maybe from my guilt.</p> <p>It's a good thing I ran, because a bullet whizzes by over top. Just before I flicker, I hear a voice behind me.</p> <p>&quot;You poor fool, Myrtle. You really do not know the border lands.&quot;</p> <p>Daisy is on the other side, where it's cold and the land is dotted with  the closest thing we ever get to trees here. I don't know if he followed me, and Daisy for once doesn't complain when I jump on her back and run. I don't know if he followed me, this man who I saw die, but I've lost him for now.</p> <h1 class="subtitle">God's Gonna Cut You Down</h1> <p>I'm a baker. I have gotten in a big fight with someone, many years ago, and they're now the mayor. Now my fight is everyone's fight, and people are quietly picking sides. </p> <h2 class="subsubtitle">Chapter 1</h2> <div class="notes"><p>Note that the 3 numbers below are from a table for 3d6's. A d666 table, some would say. Lol. I'm going to leave out listing the threads, they're mostly useful while you're writing and I only have the final version for each chapter.</p></div> <p><em>Verse 1: 5:3:4 feed the poor</em></p> <p>On a whim, I give free bread to Anne, whose farm is struggling. She goes from being cold and distant to friendly and grateful. Word gets around and I give bread to those in need. I can't keep it up forever, but I'm winning some of the town back.</p> <p><em>Verse 2: 4:2:3 restore what you deceitfully gained</em></p> <p>I realize that I have mistakenly underpaid the miller. The miller is the mayor's cousin. I reluctantly admit that I have overpaid him and give him the money back, hoping to bolster my reputation by my honesty. Instead he accuses me of being just afraid of angering the mayor. Rumours spread that I was deceitful in my business dealings.</p> <p><em>Verse 3: 6:2:4 don't break vows</em></p> <p>I had promised Anne free bread, and don't have the flour for it. But a promise is a promise. I tell her this will have to the be last time.</p> <p><em>Verse 4: 2:2:2 don't steal/lie/deal falsely</em></p> <p>My old friend the Salesman is back in town. This time he has a grift - he's selling snake oil. He offers to cut me in on it if I can sell it in my shop. I desperately need the money but I can't prove the mayor right and stoop to such dishonesty.</p> <p><em>Verse 5: 3:2:6 another one about mercy and truth</em></p> <p>Anne's son is sick and is trying to buy the snake oil from the Salesman in the inn. I know she can't afford it. I reveal what he said to me in front of the whole town. I've made an enemy.</p> <p><em>Verse 6. 4:3:1 (false witness)</em> - <b>failed!</b></p> <p>My son sets fire to the bakery. Insurace won't pay out if it's him. I say I saw the Salesman do it. The timing is right. People believe it. He flees in the night.</p> <h2 class="subsubtitle">Chapter 2</h2> <p><b><i>A few weeks later...</i></b></p> <p><em>Verse 1: 5:6:6 Swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath</em></p> <p>The mayor makes a speech against dishonest merchants. He is clearly targeting me. The Miller implies I set the fire on purpose to scam insurance. I say nothing. I don't even acknowledge it.</p> <p><em>Verse 2: 3:3:3  Love the stranger</em></p> <p>A new person comes into town. They seem disreputable, they come in with a bullet wound. People in the community don't want him here, they want him to move on. He comes to me for help specifically - he heard from a beggar I gave out free bread. I help him with great reluctance.</p> <p><em>Verse 3: 2:5:5 Thine own friend, and father's friend, forsake not</em></p> <p>My son confesses to me that he set the fire, he is afraid that I blamed my friend by mistake and that he set us apart. He wants to go find him and bring him some of the gold. I, too, am feeling guilty, and the mysterious stranger has given me an equally mysterious sum of gold, so I can afford it now. I send him off with my blessing.</p> <p><em>(oops I've been doing wrong number of dice)</em></p> <p><em>Verse 4: 1:6:4 (don't partake of other men's sins)</em> -  <strong>failed!</strong></p> <p>It turns out the stranger is a wanted man, and someone comes looking for him. He tells me that if he is found at my house, I will be ruined, everyone will think  me a criminal - and I think of the mayor and how he'd use this. I just need to help him escape. So I do. I hear gunfire that night, and try not to think about it.</p> <h2 class="subsubtitle">Chapter 3</h2> <p>It's been a month and my son is still missing.</p> <p><em>Verse 1: 5:6:5 Redeem firstborn son</em></p> <p>(Wow, this is way too appropriate)</p> <p>I hear my son was arrested. It is he, not I, who is now being blamed: he had the stolen gold, and he confessed to the Salesman that I lied about who set the fire.</p> <p>The Salesman writes me a letter. My son will go to prison if I don't go. I go.</p> <p><em>Verse 2: 5:3:5 Do not bear a grudge</em></p> <div class="notes"> <p>At this point I realized why the mayor and the protagonist hate each other. I realized that a wife has been notably missing this entire story. Maybe she died in childbirth, and the mayor had some connection to her, and blames the protagonist for what happened. I feel like the protagonist must be at fault here in other people's eyes for this confict to make sense - I think he had a child out of wedlock and refused to marry her.</p> </div> <p>Before I go, I go to the mayor and I apologize. I say that I was wrong, many years ago, and more wrong to hold onto my anger. The mayor is overcome with sadness. Things could have been so different, so many years ago. I don't know what has happened to you to give you some capacity for self-reflection. I tell him I'm leaving town and I hope to be back but I don't know if I will. I tell him I am going to get my son back. He tells me that looking after my son is the one decent thing I've done in my life and not to bother returning if I don't return with my son. I get him to promise that if my son comes back alone, he will look after him.</p> <p><em>Verse 3: 6:1:5 thou shall not kill</em> - <b>failed!</b></p> <p>(Another overly approriate one. Though it was my second roll, I skipped the first one, I don't remember what it was but it was too similar to a previous one.)</p> <p>The trial of my son is tomorrow. I meet the Salesman. We have a bitter argument. He says I'm the worst kind of hypocrite, willing to destroy anyone to make myself look better. This is not how I imagined it going. I finally tell him that I'll admit to letting him take the fall for the fire, to free my son, but too many words have been said. The Salesman shrugs and says, like father, like son, it wasn't an accident, I know you burned it down for the insurance. You sent your son with blood money, you threw me under the bus to distract from your dealings with bandits and murderers. I pull out a knife and stab him. They would hang me either way, and now I get to tell the story.</p> <p>My son goes free.</p> <p>I think in my last night about how all my troubles started with that first sin, against Emilia, so many years ago. How as a young man I was foolish and thoughtless. How I tried to be a good father, but my anger at the mayor - my shame - kept me from doing so. And how I let that shame fester and grow larger and larger until it killed people, and finally me.</p>]]>
    </description>
    <category>Play Report</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, August 10, 2024</pubDate>
  </item>


    <item>
    <title>20 Virtues And/Or Vices</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/wip/values.html</link>
    <description> <![CDATA[<h2 class="title">20 Virtues And/Or Vices</h2> <p><i>Recently, I wrote a different blog post that gave some background context behind me writing this, <a href="../discourse/problem_with_alignment.html"> here.</a></i></p> <p>I've been working on my own quasi-alignment system for well over a year now and I'm pretty happy about how it's been able to create NPCs (and PCs) with interesting motivations. It consists of 20 values in 10 opposing pairs, which I tried to phrase neutrally, and which I hope could characterize either a protagonist or an antagonist. I mostly have created it with fantasy adventure games in mind, although it's probably more universally applicable.</p> <p>The complete list:</p> <ol> <li><a href="#mercy"> Mercy vs Ruthlessness</a></li> <li><a href="#courage">Courage vs Prudence</a></li> <li><a href="#cunning"> Cunning vs Honesty</a></li> <li><a href="#ambition">Ambition vs Humility</a></li> <li><a href="#impartiality"> Impartiality vs Loyalty</a> </li> <li><a href="#sacrifice">Self-Sacrifice vs Survival</a></li> <li><a href="#passion">Passion vs Stoicism</a></li> <li><a href="#asceticism">Asceticism vs Extravagance</a></li> <li><a href="#frankness">Frankness vs Propriety</a></li> <li><a href="#novelty">Novelty vs Tradition</a></li> </ol> <h3 class="subtitle">How To Use</h3> <p>While you could go down the list and pick one of each, I find it's easier to make and portray a memorable character if you pick a small number that are important to them. I typically roll a few times. A d20, with 1-10 being the first part of the pair and 11-20 being the second allows you to randomly select a few. I usually do two values for NPCs and three for PCs. Picking just one tends to make characters that are, well, one-dimensional. I skip any repeats or any opposite pairs.</p> <p>The first 6 are probably more deeply held values, with the last 4 being more something that can set the style, look, or attitude of the NPC, so you could instead roll a d12 and just consider the first 6. Or roll a d12 for one of the values and a d20 for the other.</p> <p>Another option is to roll a 1d10 and pick based on what makes sense for the character. A classic heroic story might have the heroes always choose mercy over ruthlessness and courage over pragmatism, for instance.</p> <p> <b>Factions:</b> I'll often also give one or two values for factions. Individual members of the faction might vary, but groups as a whole can have shared values. An order of knights might value courage and self-sacrifice, but the particular knight you meet might seem largely motivated by ambition.</p> <p><b>Reaction rolls:</b> A quick and easy social mechanic can be that matching values result in a positive reaction, and clashing values result in a negative reaction.  It oversimplifies the breadth of human experience, but so do any social mechanics.  Alternately, you could have it modify reaction rolls. Roll twice and take the higher if the values match, roll twice and take the lower if they clash. Then any result is still possible but shared values skews the results. <h3 class="subtitle">More On Each Set Of Values</h3> <p><i>This part is way too long, but I need to stop spending time on this and get the blog post out.</i></p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="mercy">Mercy vs Ruthlnessnes</h4> <p>I've been struggling a lot with the second word; I'm looking for something both neutral and specific.</p> <p>Do the ends justify the means? Do your enemies deserve a second chance, or will sparing them only lead to further evil? Someone who believes in mercy might see their opposites as cruel, and someone who believes in ruthlesness might see their opposites as weak or naive.</p> <p>Protagonists who embody mercy could be healers, pacifists (religious or otherwise), or rogues who use stealth to avoid violence. Those who embody ruthlessness are probably antiheroes: they  might be assassins, the person you call in when a hard but necessary task is needed; revolutionaries or those otherwise forced to exist in a ruthless environment. When they coexist in a party, there might be a tension between the two, but an understanding that different methods are needed at different times, and maybe a certain amount of pretending to not know what is happening.</p> <p>Ruthless villains are sort of the default, but if this comes up, maybe they are willing to kill the party for relatively trivial reasons. A merciful antagonist might be a knight who insists on fighting everyone who wants to cross the bridge, but not to the death; a hive-mind of strange beings that decides you will be happier if you are absorbed into the colony and never allowed to leave; a king who is in denial about the harm he is causing and refuses to let anyone speak of any such unpleasantness.</p> <p>This is one where the exact meaning of the values should be in line with your table's boundaries as to what to play in a game.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="courage">Courage vs Prudence</h4> <p>Someone who believes in courage might see prudence as cowardice, and someone who believes in prudence might see courage as foolishness, recklessness or irresponsibility.</p> <p>Protagonists who embody courage might include berserkers, monster-hunters, or rogues performing extreme feats of acrobatics. Adventurers necessarily lean somewhat towards courage, but someone embodying prudence might be forced into adventuring through circumstance, or have learned through hard-won experience that prudence is the secret to a long adventuring career. Magic-users or stealthy hunters might better embody prudence. When coexisting in a party, it makes sense for each to fall into roles that take advantage of their predispositions.</p> <p>An antagonist who exemplifies courage might fight until the last breath; glorify warfare as an end in and of itself, or might be an automaton incapable of self-preservation. An antagonist who exemplifies prudence might be a mastermind who plots behind the scenes, or one who only ever fights from a position of strength, falling apart if they are ever outnumbered.</p> <p>In the context of adventuring this is mostly physical courage, but courage (and prudence) can take other forms in other settings. This is also one where courage could take different dimensions: a brave fighter may be afraid to take an unpopular moral stand. Interpret this as whatever form of courage is most relevant to your setting.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="cunning">Cunning vs Honesty</h4> <p>An honest character might place a lot of stock in their word or in their honour; a cunning one is willing to use lies and deception.  Think Gawain vs Loki or Odysseus. A cunning character might see an honest one as naive or gullible; a honest one might see a cunning character as dishonest.</p> <p>Protagonists who are cunning are more likely to fall into a trickster archetype. Rogues, illusionists and performers might be cunning, whereas warriors who adhere to a code of honour are often depicted as honest. Religious figures are often expected to be honest. There are a lot of stories which pair an honest and cunning character together for comic effect, which might be good inspiration for how characters with opposite values can get along.</p> <p>Antagonists who embody honesty might be supernatural beings incapable of lying; they might find it amusing to keep the letter but not the spirit of their word; they might implacably hunt the party down because they broke an oath; or they might think a strict code of honour is a substitute for morality. Antagonists who use cunning might use traps or spies; they might be monsters that mimic the player's voices; they might be supernatural beings with very dangerous ideas of a funny prank.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="ambition">Ambition vs Humility</h4> <p>Ambitious characters strive for power (magical, political, or otherwise), wealth, fame, status, respect or personal excellence, and might look down on those who don't seek those things. A character that values humility has no desire to seek these things, and might be distainful or untrusting of those who do. They might have a more egalitarian outlook, or believe that everyone should stay in their proper place in the existing hierarchies of the world.</p> <p>An adventurer who exemplifies ambition might be actively working towards wealth or power: ruling over a domain, acqurining powerful magic, or making pacts with dangerous beings. Many level-based games assume a certain level of ambition, and so if you pick this one, have it be somewhat more than the baseline. An adventurer exemplifying humility might have devoted their life to a religious order; they could be a rogue openly distainful of nobility; a druid who views the ambitions of human society as frivolous. Different attitudes towards this value don't have to clash if everyone respects each other's paths in life.</p> <p>An antagonist motivated by ambition might be trying to take over the world (or kingdom, or town); they might be trying to unlock powerful magic better left alone; they could be friendly competitors who keep showing up at every turn to try and snatch away a goal only one group can achieve. An antagonist motivated by humility could be a spirit that punishes hubris; an official who thinks the party needs to be shown their proper place in the kingdom; cultists who seek to have everyone bow to the will of their god.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="impartiality">Impartiality vs Loyalty</h4> <p>Loyal characters put their friends, family, community, leader or organization ahead of the rest of the world, whereas impartial characters treat everyone equally. Loyalty is an often overlooked motivation for a group to stick together given any other obvious reason.</p> <p>Loyal characters have a strong reason to stick together as an adventuring party; impartial characters need another reason, such as duty or money. They might be a mercenary, or be here because it's their job and they've been assigned to this task. Criminal organizations traditionally stick together through loyalty enforced by violence.</p> <p>A loyal antagonist could be a henchperson, a closely knit group of evil friends, someone from a different community who hates your community, a monster who kills anyone who it things has wronged its unwitting friend, or an otherwise noble knight who tragically feels obliged to follow an evil lord. An impartial antagonist might demonstrate equal cruelty to their followers as to the players; or mercenaries who will oppose you as long as they get paid; a monster that attacks both you and your enemies equally; a literal force of nature; an unbribeable judge who is determined to bring the party to justice for their misdeeds.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="sacrifice">Self-Sacrifice vs Survival</h4> <p>A self-sacrificing character is willing to suffer or even be willing to die for what they think is important. A character focused on survival is, well, focused on survival, which might include a loved one or close family members.</p> <p>A protagonist who embodies self-sacrifice may be more of a traditional hero, or they may have given up a lot for power. One who embodies survival may be more of an anti-hero if they're in a high-powered fantasy setting: they might have a backstory where they have had to survive, or a well-meaning mercenary. In a post-apocalyptic or horror setting, being oriented towards survival may be more the default.</p> <p>An antagonist motivated by survival might be focused on trying to extend their life,  or be some kind of monster that is only dangerous because it feels threatened, or be someone who betrayed you to protect their family. An antagonist motivated by self-sacrifice might be a fanatic devoted to a greater cause, or they may have made a terrible bargain for power. They could be creatures that explode on contact or otherwise die like bees to protect a larger group.</p> <p>There are some similarities with courage vs prudence. But a prudent advisor, say, might always advise avoiding risk, and then when their advice is ignored, stick around to help out until the very end. A brave mercenary might do any job for the right price, as long as there's a chance of survival, but they're gone as soon as the money stops coming.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="passion">Passion vs Stoicism</h4> <p>Passionate characters express emotions freely and exhuberantly, and might see those who don't as untrustworthy or insufficiently sincere. Calm characters value control over their emotions and might see their opposites as immature.</p> <p>In terms of fantasy archetypes, barbarians and bards would generally be more passionate, whereas monks and paladins are more stoic. Magic-users might use passion to power their magic, or be required to be stoic to remain control. This and the remaining ones are somewhat less serious as values go, and so while you might play up character differences for comedy, there is no reason that within a party they would have to cause conflict.</p> <p>A passionate antagonist might be a villain who flies into a terrible rage; a supernatural being whose songs leave you transfixed by sadness or your mind clouded by ecstatic joy, or an immortal undead who staves off the boredom of eternity with cruelty. A stoic antagonist might be an icy cold tyrant; a supernatural being that doens't understand your pain or fear; a religious figure who views strong feelings as weakness that leads to evil.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="asceticism">Asceticism vs Extravagance</h4> <p>Ascetic characters take pride in needing very little of the comforts of life. They might dress simply, own few things, prefer a lack of ornament, eat plain food, and abstain from drink or other intoxicants. An extravagant character might wear elaborate clothing, be fond of food or drink, or the other comforts of life. They may not necessarily pursue all of these: they could be a wealthy noble, or like the hobbits eat 6 meals a day, or spend every coin as soon as they get it.</p> <p>In terms of fantasy archetypes, some religious figures might be expected to wear plain clothing and live plain lives, whereas others might wear elaborate vestments or hold feasts for the glory of their gods. A druid might distain the comforts of civilization, or believe that you should enjoy the bounty of the natural world as much as possible. A knight might revel in the wealth of their position or believe that a spartan lifestyle strengthens their ability to fight. </p> <p>Extravagance can be a good motivation for a more heist-themed game: trying to steal the most elaborate cake, most beautiful cape, or rarest wine for instance can be more of a fun premise than just stealing money. Conversely, a more ascetic character might grow dissatisfied with the luxuries of living in a house like a normal person and feel driven to go seek out  the simplicity and even discomfort of adventuring life.</p> <p>An ascetic villain might include religious extremists, a frighteningly disciplined army, a miserly lord who hoards the taxes extracted from peasants, or a lich contemptuous of your weak and fleshy bodies. Good extravagant villains might include a vampire count, a greedy lord who wastes the taxes extracted from peasants, an elven court or a rival bard.</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="frankness">Frankness vs Propriety</h4> <p>Someone who values frankness might see the other as being dishonest or insincere; someone who values propriety might see the other as being rude or boorish. Propriety is likely to be valued when meeting the king; frankness might be valued more in the barracks. People often switch between these to some degree as needed, but others firmly stick to one or the other.</p> <p>In protagonists, this probably depends more on your background than anything else. Courtiers, diplomats and merchants are more likely to value propriety, but frankness might mean you have the status to get away with speaking your mind. Warriors and others for whom power comes from action rather than speech might tend to be more frank, or they migh speak more carefully because an insult can lead to death. Magic and religion might require precise, careful and polite speech.</p> <p>A villain who values propriety could be in a court full of intrigue and backstabbing, or the court of the fey where rudeness can lead to death. They could be someone who prefers to couch what they do in euphemisms. A villain who values frankness might respect the party for insulting them to their face (but still intend to kill them).</p> <h4 class="subsubtitle" id="novelty">Novelty vs Tradition</h4> <p>Do you stay in your hometown or always want to see what is over the next horizon? Do you stick to the traditional obligations of your role or break from them? </p> <p>A protagonist motivated by tradition might be a member of an ancient order or religion. They may have traveled far from home but keep to the things they learned in their childhood. Dwarves in fantasy often exemplify this. A protagonist motivated by novelty may have left their home out of wanderlust or a desire to see the world. They could clash with the expectations of where they grew up - for instance, a noble who ran away from home because court protocol was stifling, or someone who left town so they would not be forced to take over the family business.</p> <p>An antagonist who values tradition might be hunting down one of the adventurers to make them adhere to an unwanted role; they might be an undead being who is determined to return the world to how it was 1000 years ago; a village where human sacrifice is just how they've always done things. A villain who values novelty could be a dragon that collects people like people used to collect butterflies, a wizard with a terrible new invention, or a monster that eats brains to absorb your experiences.</p> <p>As a side note, this is a tricky one to give serious examples for, especially for antagonists who value novelty, because the notion of tradition vs novelty exists in the context of us living in the modern world, to some degree. In the past this might have manifested as a genuine belief that people should not step outside of the expectations of tradition and society. I don't think this is a likely attitude of player characters, though. Starting maybe with Mary Shelley's Frankenstein, though, you start getting different attitudes about changes happening in society due to science or otherwise. Much as Tolkien denies it, LotR is probably in part about the industrialization of war, contrasted with the nostalgic and pastoral life of the hobbits. Or you could keep this confict as a set of minor character traits. </p> <h3 class="subtitle">Poll results and more on develolping this list</h3> <p>To get some idea as to whether these alignments make sense, I <a href="https://dice.camp/deck/@seedling/112859101086002106"> asked on mastodon which one people think apply to them.</a> I had about 25-35 answers on each question, and I got enough balance that I'm happy with it: </p> <ul> <li>Courage vs Prudence: 62% vs 38%</li> <li>Honesty vs Cunning: 61% vs 39%</li> <li>Ambition vs Humility: 20% vs 80%</li> <li>Loyalty vs Impartiality: 42% vs 58%</li> <li>Mercy vs Ruthlessness: 79% vs 21%</li> <li>Self-sacrifice vs Survival: 40% vs 60%</li> <li>Passion vs Calm: 40% vs 60%</li> <li>Asceticism vs Extravagance: 54% vs 46%</li> <li>Propriety vs Frankness: 29% vs 71%</li> <li>Tradition vs Novelty: 28% vs 72%</li> </ul> <p>The least balanced one is ambition vs humility, followed by mercy vs ruthlesnness. These conflicts might be more prominent in stories than in real life, and these are two I feel I have to inclue regardless. </p> <p>For the approximately 70/30 ones, we had propriety vs frankness and tradition vs novelty. I think this split is reflective of the values of the culture that I personally exist in, rather than a universal trend. For the rest I was pleased to see a more even split. These included some of the ones I was most afraid I had just made up, so I'm glad to see that they divide people in real life as well.</p> <p>I cut two since when I started: one was &quot;wisdom vs innocence&quot; - I was trying to get at how some cultures value youth more (ours tends to, to some degree) and others value age more, but I felt it was both hard to convey in one word as well as hard to make it actually appear in how an individual character behaves.</p> <p>The other one I cut was was justice vs - well I couldn't quite find a second word. Accepting things as they are. The desire to change the world for the better vs the belief that the current nature of things are unavoidable. Between struggling to find a way to concisely articulate the concept, and the fact that it has some overlap with other values, meant I decided to cut it, conveniently leaving the final list at 20.</p>]]>
  </description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Tue, Aug 6 2024</pubDate>
  </item>


    <item>
    <title>The Problem With Classical Alignment As Character Traits</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/discourse/problem_with_alignment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[<p><i>Hopefully I remain sufficiently obscure that this post doesn't break containment and make a lot of people angry. If it does I only accept replies on Mastodon, or as blog posts but only if I happen to follow your blog already.</i></p> <h2 class="title">The Problem With Classical Alignment As Character Traits</h2> <p>Originally I was writing a totally different blog post. I still am, but that blog post got so out of hand that I had to break the part about why I'm writing it at all into another blog post.</p> <p>I don't think that Good vs Evil or Law vs Chaos are useful ways of defining characters unless you are playing an extremely specific type of game. As values, these are so broad as to be useless in characterizing anyone, and also inherently impossible to define in a way everyone can agree on.</p> <p><b>The problem with Good and Evil:</b> Most people would agree that their values are Good and values unlike theirs are Evil, by definition. Prominent figures in RPG history have definitively stated that certain actions are Good which I would consider unambiguously Evil. If anyone ever describes their values as being Evil they are usually doing so to be subversive or rebellious, usually to oppose an authority who has the power to define Good and is using that power for evil. You can tell stories about an evil villain who enthusiastically embraces evil for no particular reason, but that isn't usually what people are interested in most of the time. </p> <p><b>The problem with Law and Chaos:</b> This seems like the more interesting and sophisticated pair, but that is only because Law and Chaos are so impossible to define as to be meaningless. Ok, so barbarians are chaotic because they live outside of society's norms. But which society's norms? Presumably not their own. Lawful Good characters uphold the law (unless the law is unjust) and Chaotic Good characters oppose unjust laws - but this seems to say more about the quality of the laws than anything. If Lawful characters adhere to a strict internal code, people who are opposed to authority can have some of the strictest moral codes. And if you define "Chaos" as "acts randomly and for no reason", then Chaotic characters are both annoying and unrealistic. Law and Chaos define an assortment of different spectrums of values that can be in opposition to each other. </p> <p>The one way that a Law vs Chaos axis can be interesting is if Law and Chaos are fundamental forces of the universe, rather than character traits. I tihnk it's even possible for Good and Evil to be interesting in the same way, but only if they are slightly disjoint from actual morality. Consider Good Omens as an example of this. Or maybe taken farther, His Dark Materials.</p> <p>I actually think the 9 square classic alignment chart has remained popular precisely because it is so confusing and ambiguous. You can argue about what it means to be Good or Evil or Lawful or Chaotic forever. Because it's a topic that is very good at generating endless Internet arguments with no possible conclusion, it has an outsized footprint on the larger TTRPG culture.</p> <h3 class="subtitle">Do you have an alternate suggestion?</h3> <p>I do in fact, I have a blog post that I'm writing, but it has grown out of control to the extent that this blog post is actually broken out of the draft of the other one. Although, to be honest, I made this list because a lot of other people have made lists of values to define characters, and I haven't been satisfied with any of them.</p> <p>These are the goals I had in mind when defining this one:</p> <ol> <li>Values should be relatively objective. Of couse it's impossible for values to be truly objective, but people are generally going to have an easier time agreeing on what &quot;impartial&quot; means and what such a character might look like, versus &quot;good&quot;.</li> <li>Values should result in interesting, complex characters.</li> <li>Arbitrary combinations of values should be both plausible and interesting.</li> <li>Each value should be able to produce both a protagonist and an antagonist, and should be phrased in a way someone might describe themselves.</li> <li>There should be real life people who align with each, and who would be proud of doing so.</li> <li>Opposing values should clash, and it should feel natural that they clash. They should generate conflicts that feel natural and human.</li> </ol> <p>I did not try to make all the values have the same level of seriousness. I didn't try and make them be topics I personally am neutral on either, even if I try to describe them neutrally.</p> <p>I brainstormed ideas by a mix of thinking of the cultures and subcultures, past and present, that I'm aware of, including religious and political cultures, supplemented by a lot of reading Wikipedia. I came up with 24, which after about a year I have narrowed down to 20 that I like, a convenient number to pick from randomly using commonly used dice. </p> <h3 class="subtitle">The complete list</h3> <ol> <li>Mercy vs Ruthlessness</li> <li>Courage vs Prudence</li> <li>Cunning vs Honesty</li> <li>Ambition vs Humility</li> <li>Impartiality vs Loyalty</li> <li>Self-Sacrifice vs Survival</li> <li>Passion vs Stoicism</li> <li>Asceticism vs Extravagance</li> <li>Frankness vs Propriety</li> <li>Novelty vs Tradition</li> </ol> <p>This is still a bit of a work in progress. I feel like these require some explanation (coming soon in a later blog post). But I think it is already apparent just from reading this that meaningful conflict can stem from these values. For instance, I expect the reception to this post to relate to differing values with regards to <i>Tradition</i> and <i>Novelty</i>. </p>]]>
  </description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Aug 4 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thoughts on Tome of Tombs and 1400 </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/other_games/tome_of_tombs_1400.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>This is the second in my <a href="glide_first_impressions.html">extremely infrequent</a> series of not-reviews. I don't consider myself a proper reviewer, and I'm not going to talk about games I don't like. I will maybe give some idea of whether or not you might like the game too.</p> <p>These games have nothing to do with each other, they are grouped into one blog post because of the physical proximity of the two in my zine pile.</p> <h2 class="title">1400</h2> <p>So I haven't actually played any 24xx game. I really want to, but I want someone else to GM it, so it might be a while. So take my thoughts with a grain of salt.</p> <p>You might like this if:</p> <ul> <li>You're an experienced GM and your players are new to RPGs and want something simple and easy to learn</li> <li>You're an experienced GM and you want something that is very rules lite, but not necessarily ItO style</li> <li>You have been playing 5E but you &quot;almost never roll the dice&quot;</li> </ul> <p>You might not like this if</p> <ul> <li>You aren't very comfortable improvising or making rulings based off of fairly sparse text</li> <li>You're a strict classic OSR type</li> <li>You want a lot of character options or tactical complexity</li> </ul> <p>I got this mostly because I wanted a physical copy of a 24xx game, but I think if I had to run one, I would feel most comfortable running this, since I know what a fantasy game looks like, and you could probably run a lot of different modules based on it.</p> <p>There are really 5 games in here, each of which cover a genre.</p> <ul> <li>QUEST - kind of generic, default fantasy. Feels like it's meant to be a replacement for mainstream D&amp;D like 5E: the setting feels high fantasy, you ignore minor transactions. I feel like people might want slightly more variation in character ancestry - if I was playing with 5E players I would probbly borrow from PLANES.</li> <li>BELOW - more OSR-y, a focus on dungeon crawling</li> <li>SNEAK feels like it captures a lot of the essence of BitD - BitD is a complicated system, and I wonder how using this system to play in Duskvol would work. It dips a bit into what I think of story game mechanics: flashbacks in particular. I mostly thought of 24XX as being OSR-adjacent but I guess it doesn't have to be. Or maybe those two things aren't so different from each other. The implied setting is more classic fantasy though with liches and elves and all that</li> <li>MAGE - not totally sure what this is a reference to, but high powered, everyone-is-a-wizard fantasy seems like an obvious genre people would want to play</li> <li>PLANES - it's planescape . Well sort of. Whatever genre that is. It also feels kind of fresh. There is some inspiration from The Golden Compass series. It does not feel very  much like Troika. There are some interesting planes in there.</li> </ul> <p>All magic etc items, spells, etc are like 1-2 words. You'd have to agree together on what it means.</p> <p>There are some interesting rules for mixing and matching backgrounds from different games - I think I personally would only do it to a limited degree.</p> <p>There's an adventure in the back that is supposed to be playable with all 5 games. I feel like for some of the games though they would shine best if you took them in a different direction.</p> <h2 class="title">Tome of Tombs</h2> <p>You might like this if:</p> <ul> <li>You love worldbuilding</li> <li>You get a bit carried away with prep and you think going deep into the social background of funerary practices would be nice</li> <li>You want to find ways to add more interesting and complex lore to your dungeons</li> </ul> <p>You might not like this if:</p> <ul> <li>You're looking for something super focused on gameability</li> <li>You're looking for what you might traditionally think of a dungeon generation tool</li> </ul> <p>One big problem with books of random tables is that it's hard to tell if the random tables are good or not. Often they are generic, things you could have come up with yourself. The ones in this book are good: unique, interesting, and grounded in historical knowledge that I don't have. It's a book that helps flesh out a world and makes it more real; it's not 100% focused on what to bring to the table, as it says explicitly on one of the pages. It's also an enjoyable read.</p> <p>There are a series of pages starting from how the tombs might fit into society, to how it looks visually approaching them, to the grave goods and methods of burial. Some entries on different tables mesh with each other better than others, you'll want to use your judgement in how many tables to roll on and which ones. I tried just doing one thing from each table and it didn't quite work.</p> <p>I think the author did their own art and it's quite nice.</p> <p class="subtitle">Putting together a tomb</p> <p>The graves are in the center of the community: the town square where official government events happen. The path there is marked with statues of gods of the underworld. The plaza however is no longer in use: it was part of a system of government that is no longer relevant.</p> <p>The gate to the cemetery is decorated with mythical figures representing the guardians of the land of the dead. The cemetery consists of orderly bodies in rows, unmarked, under the flagstones. If you were to dig them up you would find jumbled bones, stripped of their flesh before being buried. The area is behind tall stone walls, and it is always cold here. The sun shines dimly in the sky, as though from further away than normal.</p> <p>On one side is a shrine, with small clay statues perhaps representing the deceased buried under the flagstones. Small bowls for offerings now stand empty. On the other is a mausolem whch is a small model of a palace which once stood in the city.</p> <p>To enter the mausoleum you enter through the carved jaws of an enormous primordial snake. Inside are rooms full of jars of grain, chests of bolts of cloth, each sealed with a fading scroll: if you could read it, you would see these are tax records, the last year of taxes that were still owed to the king after death.</p> <p>Continue further and it opens into a cave, a strangely natural structure, older than anything here. Wards have been carved onto the walls in languages older than the ones who built this cemetery - wards as a barrier between worlds - but some have been symbolically broken.</p> <p>A single body is on an elaborate raised platform, decorated with gold and jewels. They were buried in a simple shroud, though, which is almost entirely rotted away. The head has been embalmed, however, and rests beneath a stone mask. They were buried holding a steel staff, it seems.</p> <p>Spectres are often found around the complex, though they cannot pass through the outer gate so long as it is closed. This is a place where you can pass from the land of the dead to the land of the living, or vice versa.</p> <p>Other interested parties:</p> <ul> <li>A demon who is here to round up some loose souls is actually pretty friendly, so long as you don't interfere.</li> <li>Some supposed heirs of the old royal dynasty are looking for the Staff of Command, said to be buried here, which will allow them to retake their throne.</li> <li>Cultists seek to break open the walls between the land of the living and the land of the dead</li> </ul>]]></description>
    <category>Not Review</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, July 21 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

    <item>
    <title>Cairn solo actual play part 2 </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/actualplay/cairn_april_13_2024.html</link>
    <description>A writeup of a solo Cairn game, testing out custom rules for character generation and relationships, dealing with factions, and slowly turning into an elf because you ventured into the wrong forest.</description>
    <category>Play Report</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, April 14 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>All The Doors I Could Think Of </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/wip/all_the_doors.html</link>
    <description>A blog post version of my Door Jam(b) entry: a large list of doors.</description>
    <category>Playable</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, April 13 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

            <item>
    <title>GMing is like hosting a potluck </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/discourse/how_to_gm.html</link>
    <description>GMing a game is a special responsibility, but everyone should be able to do it, and you're probably stressing about it too much.</description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Tue, Mar 19 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

          <item>
    <title>On Door D&amp;D and its applications to solo games</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.com/blogging/discourse/door_dnd.html</link>
    <description>Some thoughts on the idea of "Door D&amp;D" (recently introduced on the podcast Between Two Cairns), why I enjoyed One Breath Left, and why solo games often blur the line between types of TTRPG.</description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Jan 21 2024</pubDate>
  </item>
  
</channel>
</rss>
