<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<!--
  categories: Play Report, Playable, Misc, WIP, Worldbuilding, Not Review
-->
<channel>
  <title>Seedling Games Blog</title>
  <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blog.html</link>
  <description>On creating, publishing and playing TTRPGs. Also worldbuilding. </description>
  <language>en-ca</language>

    <item>
    <title>The Problem With Classical Alignment As Character Traits</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/discourse/problem_with_alignment.html</link>
    <description><p><i>Hopefully I remain sufficiently obscure that this post doesn't break containment and make a lot of people angry. If it does I only accept replies on Mastodon, or as blog posts but only if I happen to follow your blog already.</i></p> <h2 class="title">The Problem With Classical Alignment As Character Traits</h2> <p>Originally I was writing a totally different blog post. I still am, but that blog post got so out of hand that I had to break the part about why I'm writing it at all into another blog post.</p> <p>I don't think that Good vs Evil or Law vs Chaos are useful ways of defining characters unless you are playing an extremely specific type of game. As values, these are so broad as to be useless in characterizing anyone, and also inherently impossible to define in a way everyone can agree on.</p> <p><b>The problem with Good and Evil:</b> Most people would agree that their values are Good and values unlike theirs are Evil, by definition. Prominent figures in RPG history have definitively stated that certain actions are Good which I would consider unambiguously Evil. If anyone ever describes their values as being Evil they are usually doing so to be subversive or rebellious, usually to oppose an authority who has the power to define Good and is using that power for evil. You can tell stories about an evil villain who enthusiastically embraces evil for no particular reason, but that isn't usually what people are interested in most of the time. </p> <p><b>The problem with Law and Chaos:</b> This seems like the more interesting and sophisticated pair, but that is only because Law and Chaos are so impossible to define as to be meaningless. Ok, so barbarians are chaotic because they live outside of society's norms. But which society's norms? Presumably not their own. Lawful Good characters uphold the law (unless the law is unjust) and Chaotic Good characters oppose unjust laws - but this seems to say more about the quality of the laws than anything. If Lawful characters adhere to a strict internal code, people who are opposed to authority can have some of the strictest moral codes. And if you define "Chaos" as "acts randomly and for no reason", then Chaotic characters are both annoying and unrealistic. Law and Chaos define an assortment of different spectrums of values that can be in opposition to each other. </p> <p>The one way that a Law vs Chaos axis can be interesting is if Law and Chaos are fundamental forces of the universe, rather than character traits. I tihnk it's even possible for Good and Evil to be interesting in the same way, but only if they are slightly disjoint from actual morality. Consider Good Omens as an example of this. Or maybe taken farther, His Dark Materials.</p> <p>I actually think the 9 square classic alignment chart has remained popular precisely because it is so confusing and ambiguous. You can argue about what it means to be Good or Evil or Lawful or Chaotic forever. Because it's a topic that is very good at generating endless Internet arguments with no possible conclusion, it has an outsized footprint on the larger TTRPG culture.</p> <h3 class="subtitle">Do you have an alternate suggestion?</h3> <p>I do in fact, I have a blog post that I'm writing, but it has grown out of control to the extent that this blog post is actually broken out of the draft of the other one. Although, to be honest, I made this list because a lot of other people have made lists of values to define characters, and I haven't been satisfied with any of them.</p> <p>These are the goals I had in mind when defining this one:</p> <ol> <li>Values should be relatively objective. Of couse it's impossible for values to be truly objective, but people are generally going to have an easier time agreeing on what &quot;impartial&quot; means and what such a character might look like, versus &quot;good&quot;.</li> <li>Values should result in interesting, complex characters.</li> <li>Arbitrary combinations of values should be both plausible and interesting.</li> <li>Each value should be able to produce both a protagonist and an antagonist, and should be phrased in a way someone might describe themselves.</li> <li>There should be real life people who align with each, and who would be proud of doing so.</li> <li>Opposing values should clash, and it should feel natural that they clash. They should generate conflicts that feel natural and human.</li> </ol> <p>I did not try to make all the values have the same level of seriousness. I didn't try and make them be topics I personally am neutral on either, even if I try to describe them neutrally.</p> <p>I brainstormed ideas by a mix of thinking of the cultures and subcultures, past and present, that I'm aware of, including religious and political cultures, supplemented by a lot of reading Wikipedia. I came up with 24, which after about a year I have narrowed down to 20 that I like, a convenient number to pick from randomly using commonly used dice. </p> <h3 class="subtitle">The complete list</h3> <ol> <li>Mercy vs Ruthlessness</li> <li>Courage vs Prudence</li> <li>Cunning vs Honesty</li> <li>Ambition vs Humility</li> <li>Impartiality vs Loyalty</li> <li>Self-Sacrifice vs Survival</li> <li>Passion vs Stoicism</li> <li>Asceticism vs Extravagance</li> <li>Frankness vs Propriety</li> <li>Novelty vs Tradition</li> </ol> <p>This is still a bit of a work in progress. I feel like these require some explanation (coming soon in a later blog post). But I think it is already apparent just from reading this that meaningful conflict can stem from these values. For instance, I expect the reception to this post to relate to differing values with regards to <i>Tradition</i> and <i>Novelty</i>. </p>></description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Aug 4 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>Thoughts on Tome of Tombs and 1400 </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/other_games/tome_of_tombs_1400.html</link>
    <description><p>This is the second in my <a href="glide_first_impressions.html">extremely infrequent</a> series of not-reviews. I don't consider myself a proper reviewer, and I'm not going to talk about games I don't like. I will maybe give some idea of whether or not you might like the game too.</p> <p>These games have nothing to do with each other, they are grouped into one blog post because of the physical proximity of the two in my zine pile.</p> <h2 class="title">1400</h2> <p>So I haven't actually played any 24xx game. I really want to, but I want someone else to GM it, so it might be a while. So take my thoughts with a grain of salt.</p> <p>You might like this if:</p> <ul> <li>You're an experienced GM and your players are new to RPGs and want something simple and easy to learn</li> <li>You're an experienced GM and you want something that is very rules lite, but not necessarily ItO style</li> <li>You have been playing 5E but you &quot;almost never roll the dice&quot;</li> </ul> <p>You might not like this if</p> <ul> <li>You aren't very comfortable improvising or making rulings based off of fairly sparse text</li> <li>You're a strict classic OSR type</li> <li>You want a lot of character options or tactical complexity</li> </ul> <p>I got this mostly because I wanted a physical copy of a 24xx game, but I think if I had to run one, I would feel most comfortable running this, since I know what a fantasy game looks like, and you could probably run a lot of different modules based on it.</p> <p>There are really 5 games in here, each of which cover a genre.</p> <ul> <li>QUEST - kind of generic, default fantasy. Feels like it's meant to be a replacement for mainstream D&amp;D like 5E: the setting feels high fantasy, you ignore minor transactions. I feel like people might want slightly more variation in character ancestry - if I was playing with 5E players I would probbly borrow from PLANES.</li> <li>BELOW - more OSR-y, a focus on dungeon crawling</li> <li>SNEAK feels like it captures a lot of the essence of BitD - BitD is a complicated system, and I wonder how using this system to play in Duskvol would work. It dips a bit into what I think of story game mechanics: flashbacks in particular. I mostly thought of 24XX as being OSR-adjacent but I guess it doesn't have to be. Or maybe those two things aren't so different from each other. The implied setting is more classic fantasy though with liches and elves and all that</li> <li>MAGE - not totally sure what this is a reference to, but high powered, everyone-is-a-wizard fantasy seems like an obvious genre people would want to play</li> <li>PLANES - it's planescape . Well sort of. Whatever genre that is. It also feels kind of fresh. There is some inspiration from The Golden Compass series. It does not feel very  much like Troika. There are some interesting planes in there.</li> </ul> <p>All magic etc items, spells, etc are like 1-2 words. You'd have to agree together on what it means.</p> <p>There are some interesting rules for mixing and matching backgrounds from different games - I think I personally would only do it to a limited degree.</p> <p>There's an adventure in the back that is supposed to be playable with all 5 games. I feel like for some of the games though they would shine best if you took them in a different direction.</p> <h2 class="title">Tome of Tombs</h2> <p>You might like this if:</p> <ul> <li>You love worldbuilding</li> <li>You get a bit carried away with prep and you think going deep into the social background of funerary practices would be nice</li> <li>You want to find ways to add more interesting and complex lore to your dungeons</li> </ul> <p>You might not like this if:</p> <ul> <li>You're looking for something super focused on gameability</li> <li>You're looking for what you might traditionally think of a dungeon generation tool</li> </ul> <p>One big problem with books of random tables is that it's hard to tell if the random tables are good or not. Often they are generic, things you could have come up with yourself. The ones in this book are good: unique, interesting, and grounded in historical knowledge that I don't have. It's a book that helps flesh out a world and makes it more real; it's not 100% focused on what to bring to the table, as it says explicitly on one of the pages. It's also an enjoyable read.</p> <p>There are a series of pages starting from how the tombs might fit into society, to how it looks visually approaching them, to the grave goods and methods of burial. Some entries on different tables mesh with each other better than others, you'll want to use your judgement in how many tables to roll on and which ones. I tried just doing one thing from each table and it didn't quite work.</p> <p>I think the author did their own art and it's quite nice.</p> <p class="subtitle">Putting together a tomb</p> <p>The graves are in the center of the community: the town square where official government events happen. The path there is marked with statues of gods of the underworld. The plaza however is no longer in use: it was part of a system of government that is no longer relevant.</p> <p>The gate to the cemetery is decorated with mythical figures representing the guardians of the land of the dead. The cemetery consists of orderly bodies in rows, unmarked, under the flagstones. If you were to dig them up you would find jumbled bones, stripped of their flesh before being buried. The area is behind tall stone walls, and it is always cold here. The sun shines dimly in the sky, as though from further away than normal.</p> <p>On one side is a shrine, with small clay statues perhaps representing the deceased buried under the flagstones. Small bowls for offerings now stand empty. On the other is a mausolem whch is a small model of a palace which once stood in the city.</p> <p>To enter the mausoleum you enter through the carved jaws of an enormous primordial snake. Inside are rooms full of jars of grain, chests of bolts of cloth, each sealed with a fading scroll: if you could read it, you would see these are tax records, the last year of taxes that were still owed to the king after death.</p> <p>Continue further and it opens into a cave, a strangely natural structure, older than anything here. Wards have been carved onto the walls in languages older than the ones who built this cemetery - wards as a barrier between worlds - but some have been symbolically broken.</p> <p>A single body is on an elaborate raised platform, decorated with gold and jewels. They were buried in a simple shroud, though, which is almost entirely rotted away. The head has been embalmed, however, and rests beneath a stone mask. They were buried holding a steel staff, it seems.</p> <p>Spectres are often found around the complex, though they cannot pass through the outer gate so long as it is closed. This is a place where you can pass from the land of the dead to the land of the living, or vice versa.</p> <p>Other interested parties:</p> <ul> <li>A demon who is here to round up some loose souls is actually pretty friendly, so long as you don't interfere.</li> <li>Some supposed heirs of the old royal dynasty are looking for the Staff of Command, said to be buried here, which will allow them to retake their throne.</li> <li>Cultists seek to break open the walls between the land of the living and the land of the dead</li> </ul></description>
    <category>Not Review</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, July 21 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

    <item>
    <title>Cairn solo actual play part 2 </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/actualplay/cairn_april_13_2024.html</link>
    <description>A writeup of a solo Cairn game, testing out custom rules for character generation and relationships, dealing with factions, and slowly turning into an elf because you ventured into the wrong forest.</description>
    <category>Play Report</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, April 14 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>All The Doors I Could Think Of </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/wip/all_the_doors.html</link>
    <description>A blog post version of my Door Jam(b) entry: a large list of doors.</description>
    <category>Playable</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, April 13 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

            <item>
    <title>GMing is like hosting a potluck </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/discourse/how_to_gm.html</link>
    <description>GMing a game is a special responsibility, but everyone should be able to do it, and you're probably stressing about it too much.</description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Tue, Mar 19 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

          <item>
    <title>On Door D&amp;D and its applications to solo games</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/discourse/door_dnd.html</link>
    <description>Some thoughts on the idea of "Door D&amp;D" (recently introduced on the podcast Between Two Cairns), why I enjoyed One Breath Left, and why solo games often blur the line between types of TTRPG.</description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Jan 21 2024</pubDate>
  </item>

        <item>
    <title>Taking bits of story games and putting them into OSR (specifically pick lists)</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/discourse/osr_and_story_games.html</link>
    <description>In which I argue that we should stop dividing ourselves into arbitrary OSR vs story game factions, and how OSR random tables and story game pick lists can learn from each other.</description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Dec 17 2023</pubDate>
  </item>

        <item>
    <title>Tannic</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/actualplay/tannic_june_4.html</link>
    <description>A writeup of a solo game of Tannic, played in Cairn.</description>
    <category>Play Report</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Dec 3 2023</pubDate>
  </item>

      <item>
    <title>A very early draft of an oracle deck</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/wip/oracle_deck.html</link>
    <description>A very early draft of an oracle deck</description>
    <category>WIP</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Dec 3 2023</pubDate>
  </item>
  

      <item>
    <title>Some thoughts on rules</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/discourse/rules.html</link>
    <description>Thoughts on what rules are and what they're for, part 1</description>
    <category>Misc</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, Oct 8 2023</pubDate>
  </item>
  
  <item>
    <title>Some basics about solo games </title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/solo/why_solo_games.html</link>
    <description>Why play solo games</description>
    <category>Solo</category>
    <pubDate>Sun, June 4 2023</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>On Cities: The Bones of the City</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/worldbuilding/the_bones_of_the_city.html</link>
    <description>The city is not distinct from the wilderness</description>
    <category>Worldbuilding</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, May 26 2023</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Retiring Characters</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/writing/retiring_characters.html</link>
    <description>Some rough ideas about mechanical incentives to retire characters</description>
    <category>WIP</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, February 21 2023</pubDate>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Manoevers in Cairn</title>
    <link>https://seedlinggames.github.io/blogging/writing/cairn_manoevers.html</link>
    <description>Some rough ideas on how to use Cairn's light mechanics for more tactical conbat</description>
    <category>WIP</category>
    <pubDate>Sat, February 11 2023</pubDate>
  </item>

</channel>
</rss>
